<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Urszula Czerwinska</title>
    <description>Science &amp;#x2192; Data Science</description>
    <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 10:07:40 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 10:07:40 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Big Dive</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;

&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
    &lt;style&gt;
        .scalable {
            overflow: hidden;
        }

        .scalable iframe {
            height: 100%;
            left: 0;
            position: absolute;
            top: 0;
            width: 100%;
        }

        .scalable .scalable-content {
            height: 0;
            position: relative;
        }

        .scalable-16-9 .scalable-content {
            /* Percentage from 9 divided by 16 for ratio of 16:9. */
            padding-bottom: 56.25%;
        }

        iframe {display:block;margin:auto;width: 100%}


    &lt;/style&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;i&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big data - big unknown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;When we play with data that are not so big... &lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        Experience with big data is among top skills of a data scientist profile.  However,  it is not trivial to learn big data tools without necessary infrastructure and proper tutoring. While pursuing my PhD in Data science dealing with medium size data frames (&lt; 1G),  usually all can be processed on one machine. In order to get some taste of methods and challenges of Big Data,  I completed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bigdive.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Big Dive&lt;/a&gt; course organized by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.top-ix.org/en/home-eng/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TOP-IX&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;... but we want to get a taste of &lt;strong&gt;BIG data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/companies.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image rights TOP-IX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
       During the intense 5-week course I put in practice my Python - pandas skills and learned new libraries for &lt;b&gt;distributed computing&lt;/b&gt;,  as well as &lt;i&gt;Py&lt;b&gt;Spark&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; basics.  We also spent a significant amount of time setting up the infrastructure on &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/fr/?nc2=h_lg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;amazon aws&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mongodb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;MongoDB&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Invited keynote speakers showed us important aspects and challenges of the data science for &lt;b&gt;business and science&lt;/b&gt;. A bonus was an introduction to beautiful &lt;b&gt;visualization D3.js&lt;/b&gt;. Finally, for me the most interesting and important part of the course was a &lt;b&gt;project&lt;/b&gt; realized for one of 3 companies: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifc.org/wps/wcm/connect/corp_ext_content/ifc_external_corporate_site/home&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IFC&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://eduscopio.it/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Eduscopio&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tesisquare.com/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TesiSquare&lt;/a&gt; where in just a few days we put our best efforts to make sense of hundreds of gigabytes of data!
      

        


    &lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;h3&gt;About the course&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        
        The course took place in a group of 20 students, with STEM/linguistic/design background, mostly from Italy but there were also a few foreign folks like me. Our diversity helped a lot during the group project when each of us could bring different perspective and skillset.
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
         &lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bigdive6-WELCOME_def.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image rights TOP-IX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        In order to apply, a candidate needs to send a video explaining why he or she is a good fit for the big dive as well as state level of her/his prerequisites. 
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
        If you want to read more about the content of the course you can check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bigdive.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Big Dive website&lt;/a&gt; as well as read their great &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/christianracca/detail/recent-activity/posts/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;posts on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/christianracca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Christian Racca&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/bigdive.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bigdive_eu&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;twitter @bigdive_eu&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
        For most of the participants and for me it was the first time with Big data.  I found the possibility to face the problems and tools I don&#39;t encounter in my everyday work. The content of the course was quite densely packed and I will need some time after the course to practice new skills and read all material. Thanks to great teachers like among others &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/alexcomu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alex Comunian&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/abusedmedia/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fabio Franchino&lt;/a&gt; classes were very interactive and easy to follow. 
&lt;div class=&quot;scalable scalable-16-9&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;scalable-content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y1Zj_pOx_iE&amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;  allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;em&gt;Big Dive Yearbook 2017&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Personal highlights&lt;/h3&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;course was great &lt;b&gt;networking&lt;/b&gt; opportunity, patrner companies posted their job openings as well as a CV repository was creaed by course organisers to facilitate their job search, also otherp articipants of the course are new connextions in my professional network that can be priceless in the future&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;D3.js&lt;/b&gt; is a very powerful tool for data visualization but its learning curve is quite steep. Learning jquery and communication with a remote data server, basics of web design are necessary to create a serious final product. So if you don&#39;t want to spend a significant amount of time learning all the toolkit better go for pre-set solutions like RShiny if you know R for instance.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Dask&lt;/b&gt; library seems to be  an interesting alternative to Spark for smaller projects, the big plus is that it is using pandas vocabulary. It can be also misleading as we encountered quite a lot of problems building a set up for our data, lots of ram memory seems to be necessary and understanding how dask is dealing with our objects differently than pandas is crucial for a successful application. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Spark&lt;/b&gt; contains important differences in algorithms from R or scikit-learn implementations. Therefore testing locally and comparing to the distributed version is not a good idea and difference in performance can be significant. It is important to keep it in mind from the beginning of the project. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Github&lt;/b&gt; has some really cool project management features like issues system and wiki. Usually, it is not extensively used in academia or only as a code repository while for us the management part was really useful and handy to organize work. If you are a student you can get a &lt;a href=&quot;https://education.github.com/pack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Student Developer Pack for free&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;we got a refreshment about &lt;b&gt;ML&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;network science&lt;/b&gt;, together with some cool mini project implementations (like twitter API analysis) that can be a great starting point for a demo project one can use for its portfolio. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;field expert&lt;/b&gt; is an important part of the team. His needs should guide the analysis, it helps to make data scientist work really useful in the domain of its application &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/dataring.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/copyrights.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 

    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Data ring&lt;/b&gt; - a tool proposed by top-ix and IFC helps to plan the project and communicate within data science team and with the business partner. You can find more information about in the comprehensive handbook &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifc.org/wps/wcm/connect/22ca3a7a-4ee6-444a-858e-374d88354d97/IFC+Data+HandBook+FINAL.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DATA ANALYTICS AND DIGITAL FINANCIAL SERVICES&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;in my project, I worked with e-money transaction data and I found the problematic pretty interesting, it encouraged me to read finance and economy articles. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/final.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image rights TOP-IX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
   
        &lt;h3&gt;Final comments&lt;/h3&gt;
        
         
    &lt;p&gt; 
    Even if you cannot become an expert in big data in 5 weeks this course was a great intro to new concepts.  It was also a lot of fun,  intense immersion in Italian culture with lots of sun and pizza. Don&#39;t hesitate to contact me if you want to hear more about the course.
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bigdive.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image rights TOP-IX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Usefull links&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bigdive.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Big Dive website&lt;/b&gt;: http://www.bigdive.eu/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/christianracca/detail/recent-activity/posts/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;posts on LinkedIn&lt;/b&gt;: https://www.linkedin.com/in/christianracca/detail/recent-activity/posts/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/bigdive.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Facebook page&lt;/b&gt;: https://www.facebook.com/bigdive.eu/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bigdive_eu&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;twitter&lt;/b&gt;: @bigdive_eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kdnuggets.com/2016/04/data-science-comprehensive-guide-transition.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;post that inspired me to participate in Big DIVE : From Science to Data Science, a Comprehensive Guide for Transition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

            
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/bigdive/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/bigdive/</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hi, I am Computational Biologist</title>
        <description>&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
	&lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;


&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body&gt;

	&lt;style&gt;
		.scalable {
			overflow: hidden;
		}

		.scalable iframe {
			height: 100%;
			left: 0;
			position: absolute;
			top: 0;
			width: 100%;
		}

		.scalable .scalable-content {
			height: 0;
			position: relative;
		}

		.scalable-16-9 .scalable-content {
			/* Percentage from 9 divided by 16 for ratio of 16:9. */
			padding-bottom: 56.25%;
		}

		iframe {display:block;margin:auto;width: 100%}


	&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;/body&gt;   
&lt;section&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		&lt;blockquote&gt;Hi, I am Computational Biologist, would you hire me when I graduate (from PhD)?&lt;/blockquote&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;h3&gt;Thinking about a job&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		I am in my second year of PhD in Computational Biology / Systems Biology at Cancer Institute in France. It is almost halfway to graduation here, where PhD needs to be completed in 3-4 years, so I reckon it is a right time to find out personally how are my chances of getting a job in the &lt;b&gt;data science&lt;/b&gt; market. So I asked the question &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hi, I am Computational Biologist, would you hire me when I graduate (from PhD)?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; in many declinations to different companies. I would like to share with you my experience from four &lt;strong&gt;job fairs&lt;/strong&gt;, I attended in November in Paris. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Let me start from the end...&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;h3&gt;To make the long story short - key messages (for busy ones)&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;many companies will not know what &lt;b&gt;computational biology&lt;/b&gt; is -  so adapt your title to the company - i.e. &lt;i&gt;data analyst of biological/ genetic data / for medical sciences&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;data scientist in (biological) research&lt;/i&gt;  etc. in order to highlight your actual role &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;most of companies may not be familiar with qualities you can bring as a PhD graduate - work on communication of your transferable skills, convince them your are more than just a student that took longer to get a degree &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;you might hear that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/qualities-google-looks-for-in-job-candidates-2014-4?IR=T&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Google does want people with high &quot;cognitive ability&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; so you may think it is enough to be smart to get a position - even though your learning capability and intelligence are strong assets, &lt;b&gt;most of companies are not Google&lt;/b&gt;, they are &lt;b&gt;looking for solid skills&lt;/b&gt; that they will test in a technical interview i.e. your coding skills, your strategical thinking, situation analysis, problem solving. &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;in most cases, PhD graduates are treated the same way as fresh graduates from a master/engineer degree - it is rare there are predefined posts for PhD holders, you posses, for sure, different qualities and experience, which can be a plus, but don&#39;t wait for an applause, &lt;b&gt;be flexible&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; Programming in &lt;b&gt;R&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;Python&lt;/b&gt; or &lt;b&gt;SAS&lt;/b&gt; is the base (not a surprise) for data science&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;skills in &lt;b&gt;data visualization, database management, big data tools&lt;/b&gt; can be something that distinct you from other candidates&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;scientific writing&lt;/b&gt; and the whole communication toolbox, can also be a big plus, some companies release internal white papers and writing skills are highly valued &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;there is a huge need for skills of computational biologists in diverse projects in industry - lots of start-up with crazy ideas, challenging projects, there world is big out there &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;show you interest in a specific sector of industry, even an on-line course can be a plus, attend some meet-ups or events to feel the general ambiance and hot topics of the sector &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;ask questions and listen to HR advice - some of HR, especially in start-ups are actually working on projects that may interest you; some of them are new hires and they are happy to give you advice on how to get into the company&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;hiring procedures of companies&lt;/b&gt;, even with very similar profiles can be very different - take time to ask about hiring procedures, go to &lt;a href=https://www.glassdoor.fr/index.htm target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;glassdoor&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, reach company employees on LinkedIn &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;t is fine to submit your CV to employers before your finish your PhD — you never know — however, make sure you start &lt;b&gt;applying for jobs 6 months before the end of you PhD&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;add your non-academic experience to your CV, courses related to business. Do not put too many academic details, i.e. faculty full names, professors names — unless it is someone very well known— just speak the language they do.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;smile&lt;/b&gt;, have positive attitude - talk about your motivation for transition in a positive way&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;be cautious about your responsibilities, some companies, especially start-up would hire you to do everything related with data management, while what they need is a team of data analyst, not one PhD graduate &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;               

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The long story (for mindful ones)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	French educational system is complicated. To simplify, the university master and PhD is seen as a path exclusiv for academic career. This view is slowly changing and we hear more and more about companies hiring PhDs. Universities are also trying to promote alternative carriers organizing &#39;professional breakfasts&#39;, workshops, interview simulations or CV tuning (I have participated in some organized by &lt;a href=http://cfdip.uspc.fr/fr/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CFDiP&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=http://www.adoc-tm.com/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Adoc Talent Managment&lt;/a&gt;). There is even a &lt;a href=http://hub11.ecolearning.eu/course/doctorat-et-poursuite-de-carriere/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MOOC&lt;/a&gt; that should help PhDs orientate their careers. Also, recently title &lt;i&gt;Docteur-PhD&lt;/i&gt; has been officially recognized and there will be created a nation network for PhD holders with a yearbook and a standardized e-mail address system. 

	&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en-gb&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;fr&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Création d&amp;#39;un réseau des docteurs avec un annuaire annuel et une adresse mail : prenom.nom@phdfrance.fr &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sup_recherche&quot;&gt;@sup_recherche&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Thierry Mandon (@mandonthierry) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mandonthierry/status/800712541634560001&quot;&gt;21 November 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
	&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, PhD graduates still face big challenges entering the world of work. This is why, as a PhD student, I decided to find out a bit more about hiring companies and their requirements by participating in four job fairs organized in Paris in November.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  
	&lt;div class=&quot;scalable scalable-16-9&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;scalable-content&quot;&gt;
			&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/J6scnDFKWRI&quot;  allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;em&gt;Video of PhDTalent explaining value of PhDs for a company [FR]&lt;/em&gt;
		&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;PhDTalent fair&lt;/b&gt;, two data science fairs: &lt;a href=http://www.datajob.fr/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;DATAJOB&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=http://forumdatadays.fr/programme/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Forum Data Paris&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  and one organized at &lt;a href=http://jnum.parisdescartes.fr/job-dating/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Journée Numérique&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;i&gt;Digital Day&lt;/i&gt; at University Paris Descartes.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
			At any job fair, meetup or a conference when we introduce ourselves as Computational Biologists, it is not always clear to other people what it actually means.
		&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;As a &lt;b&gt;Computational Biologist&lt;/b&gt; working on data analysis in the context of imunno-oncology, with some additional on-line training, I believe I have most of basic knowledge asked for post of data analyst or data scientist: working in R, Machine Learning, statistics, data visualization, git. However, this is not clear for people working out of research in biology and healthcare. There are so many flavors of computational biologists, using different tools and applying them to different fields of biology, that it crucial to state clear what we actually do given the desired job. Computational biologist profile also usually comes with weak points as lack of professional experience out of academia, no professional network, little experience with business and consumers. What is sure, &lt;b&gt;most of computational biologist&lt;/b&gt;, with some additional training to broad their technical horizons and with open mind, &lt;b&gt;have very attractive profile for many industries&lt;/b&gt;.
			&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;I have spend around 1-2 h of my time at each job fair, that took place during the week office hours. Even though, I didn&#39;t manage to talk to all companies, especially the most popular, where the line were very long, I managed to leave my CV to 15 companies and talk to around 20. Here is a little summary of each job fair. 
			&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/logo_PhDTalent.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=https://www.phdtalent.org/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PhDTalent fair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				PhDTalent attracted  more than 70 companies form different industries. These could be roughly  split into three groups: Biotech / Pharma, consulting, Policy, Robotics &amp; Data science &amp; Big data &amp; IT &amp; Computing. 

				There were presented a wide variety of different job offers. Some like Orange or L&#39;Oréal recruit for their PostDocoral programs.

				During the day, I have learned that some companies, during the &lt;b&gt;recruitment process&lt;/b&gt; can send applicants a &lt;b&gt;weekly challenge&lt;/b&gt; or test through up to &lt;b&gt;7 interviews&lt;/b&gt; for a R&amp;D position. In addition, I also spoke to various start-ups that generate diverse data; they need people to manage them and sometimes they do hope one PhD can replace data management team. I also encountered even very surprising job descriptions: one start-up in particular was looking to hire &lt;b&gt;bioinformatician to model hormone detection in the air by their humanoid robot&lt;/b&gt;. I am not sure if they correctly interpreted what the skills of a bioinformatician are ;) (For those who are not sure what bioinformatician does have a look at the article in &lt;a href=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4408859/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Frontiers of Genetics: Who qualifies to be bioinformatician?&lt;/a&gt;)
			&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/DATAJOBS.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/forumdata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Jobs forum at Bourse de Paris. Image credit to &lt;a href=http://www.datajob.fr/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;datajobs.fr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
			&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=http://forumdatadays.fr/programme/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Forum Data&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=http://www.datajob.fr/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Data Jobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Those two job fairs had splendid sponsors and a wide array of known companies present.
				Even though, it was not designed solely for PhD graduates I found companies representatives very enthousiastic and helpful  - perhaps reflecting vigor for the potential that the data industry has to offer. Key things that I took home from these events were that, of course, it is too early now for me to apply being mid-way through my PhD. However they recommended looking at role descriptions on company websites and keeping an eye out for events to get involved with. For example, some firms organize their own meetups where you have the opportunity to meet employees or work on mini projects for the company. I was also advised to attend &lt;a href=https://startupweekend.org/locations/europe/fr target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;startup weekends&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where many startup present at those and similar events hire actively. When trying to gather information about data analysis positions in an established beauty company with big R&amp;D sector, I was surprised to discover that they &lt;b&gt;only&lt;/b&gt; hire PhD graduates with at least three year experience working in company (whilst hiring engineers straight away). In contrast, Other companies were also looking for three years experience. However in practice, if companies are looking for people and you interview well, you have every chance of being hired. &lt;br&gt;Therefore, I buried my hopes to stay close to biology an healthcare, and analyze biological data. Probably for a first job, one needs to be more flexible than that.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=http://jnum.parisdescartes.fr/job-dating/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Journées numériques&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Among numerous activities of &lt;i&gt;Digital Day&lt;/i&gt; there were a little job fair organized. A few number of companies presented job offers. However, the &lt;i&gt;job offers in digital expertise&lt;/i&gt; was a bit misleading and most of jobs proposed were related to advanced computing, IT management, web marketing and communication.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;h3&gt;How to choose a company?&lt;/h3&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/office.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;It is very important issue. Let&#39;s imagine, you have a great profile, desired by many companies. How do you chose the company?&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;As a foreigner in France and academia-trained I do not have clear idea about model of functioning of different companies and possible advantage and disadvantages of specific setups.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;I encountered many consulting offices, where employees work actually for different companies to solve an issue or work on a project. I was told, their offer can seem very attractive at the first sight: variety of subjects, cutting edge technologies, big companies. However, they also are some drawbacks, as employees are hired by the consulting company, they are lured by the most attractive projects, but there is no guarantee to which one they will be associated because it depends a lot on client choice, and other available consultants. On the other hand, even a short contract in a company developing new technologies such as &lt;i&gt;Orange&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;Microsoft&lt;/i&gt; can be very good for your career, while consulting job can be easier to get but will not always meet your expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

					&lt;h3&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h3&gt;
					&lt;p&gt;Career transition is probably not easy, future is not all roses, but with some determination, I am pretty sure a &lt;b&gt;Camputational Biologist has great chances to find a well-paid job outside academia&lt;/b&gt;. Job market is very competitive and demands are high. Luckily for us, programming skills combined with capacity for analysis seem to be in high demand. There will be still some knowledge gaps, some unknowns, but our duty is to turn them into challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/horizon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
					&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

				&lt;/section&gt;
				&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/jobsCB/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/jobsCB/</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From Science to Data Science</title>
        <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE HTML&gt;
&lt;html lang=&quot;en-US&quot;&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
        &lt;meta charset=&quot;UTF-8&quot;&gt;
        &lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;refresh&quot; content=&quot;1; url=&quot;&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
            window.location.href = &quot;https://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/FromSciencetoDataScience/&quot;
        &lt;/script&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Page Redirection&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
        &lt;!-- Note: don&#39;t tell people to `click` the link, just tell them that it is a link. --&gt;
        If you are not redirected automatically, follow this &lt;a href=&#39;https://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/FromSciencetoDataScience/&#39;&gt;link to example&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/FromSciencetoDataScience</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/FromSciencetoDataScience</guid>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>Careers</category>
        
        <category>Data Science</category>
        
        <category>Data viz</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
        <category>FSctoDs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Outreach</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;


&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body&gt;

     &lt;style&gt;



      &lt;/style&gt;
 
      &lt;/body&gt;  
&lt;section&gt;
	&lt;h4&gt;Certificate in Business And Administration&lt;/h4&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;I has been four years CBA at Paris Descartes train and gather together talented students from different disciplines. Network build during this two-week workshop remains a strong point of all the participants.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;If you want to find out about my experience at CBA please &lt;a href=&quot;/thoughts/CBA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;check out my post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Here are some facts and figures we prepared with some CBA representatives and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PxGirard&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pierre Girard,&lt;/a&gt; the organiser of the Part I.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 

 

&lt;div class=&#39;tableauPlaceholder&#39; id=&#39;viz1479135570783&#39; style=&#39;position: relative&#39;&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#&#39;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#39;Tableau de bord 1 &#39; src=&#39;https:&amp;#47;&amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;#47;static&amp;#47;images&amp;#47;CB&amp;#47;CBA_2&amp;#47;Tableaudebord1&amp;#47;1_rss.png&#39; style=&#39;border: none&#39; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;object class=&#39;tableauViz&#39;  style=&#39;display:none;&#39;&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;host_url&#39; value=&#39;https%3A%2F%2Fpublic.tableau.com%2F&#39; /&gt; &lt;param name=&#39;site_root&#39; value=&#39;&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;name&#39; value=&#39;CBA_2&amp;#47;Tableaudebord1&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;tabs&#39; value=&#39;no&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;toolbar&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;static_image&#39; value=&#39;https:&amp;#47;&amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;#47;static&amp;#47;images&amp;#47;CB&amp;#47;CBA_2&amp;#47;Tableaudebord1&amp;#47;1.png&#39; /&gt; &lt;param name=&#39;animate_transition&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_static_image&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_spinner&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_overlay&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_count&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;                &lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39;&gt;                    var divElement = document.getElementById(&#39;viz1479135570783&#39;);                    var vizElement = divElement.getElementsByTagName(&#39;object&#39;)[0];                    vizElement.style.width=&#39;824px&#39;;vizElement.style.height=&#39;3819px&#39;;                    var scriptElement = document.createElement(&#39;script&#39;);                    scriptElement.src = &#39;https://public.tableau.com/javascripts/api/viz_v1.js&#39;;                    vizElement.parentNode.insertBefore(scriptElement, vizElement);                &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/CBA_outreach</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/CBA_outreach</guid>
        
        <category>Tableau</category>
        
        <category>Infographic</category>
        
        <category>Communication</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data and the Future of Healthcare</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
	&lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;

&lt;/head&gt;

 &lt;body&gt;

     &lt;style&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;    	
        
		body { background-color:blue; }
		.highlightme { background-color:#ccffe5; }
 &lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;/style&gt;
 
      &lt;/body&gt;  
      &lt;section&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pebourne&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phil Bourne&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a founding Editor-in-Chief of PLOS Computational Biology and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sdsc.edu/~bourne/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Associate Director for Data Science (ADDS)&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nih.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Institutes of Health&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;His research focuses are countless: algorithms, text mining, machine learning, metalanguages, biological databases, and visualizations applied to problems in systems pharmacology, evolution, cell signaling, apoptosis, immunology and scientific dissemination coupled with education and public service.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Attendees  of ISMB 2016 in Orlando had the opportunity to interact with him at the workshop on Education in Bioinformatics (WEB) — ‘Exploiting Cloud and Virtual Resources for Training : Getting the Best Training in Computational Biology in an Era of Cloud Computing and Big Data’.&lt;/p&gt;


      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;
In this interview, Phil Bourne gives his opinion about Big Data era, the impact of data science and will impact biological research and healthcare. He also comments on frictions: between the corporate world and research, as well as formal training and citizen science. 
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;The list of your achievements and engagements is very long. Besides your academic ones, you also founded companies so you are familiar with corporate world. With regards to Data Science &amp; Big Data, it seems like there is a hype around them in companies right now. Do you think solutions developed for science can compete with the ones developed for big data with big money? Will academic and private Data Science work together or companies like Google will take a monopoly on data solutions?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Answer:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;Big data covers a big area — there is a need for government and private funder solutions, for company solutions and for hybrid solutions. Just as the market place benefits from government research that then gets translated into commercial products we will see the same with big data.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;highlightme&quot;&gt;Biomedical research and health care is a bit late in the game and has the disadvantage of not being born digital and so is relatively slow to respond.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Notwithstanding there is a lot of fundamental research which the private sector is not likely to do that will be done by government and private foundation funding and ultimately will prove to be of great value. Areas of provenance, standards, data wrangling and security are examples that come to mind.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Biological research is still under an ongoing digitization process. However an important number of wet lab biologist are still reluctant to learn how to use computational tools that would make their research more interesting and more quantitative. What message would you like to convey them?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Answer:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;The contributions of computation and other peoples data to the biomedical research enterprise cannot be ignored at this point. It should be embraced. &lt;span class=&quot;highlightme&quot;&gt;At the same time computational biologists have an obligation to make their methods and tools accessible to a broader audience.&lt;/span&gt; We need training programs that prepare students for a future where analytical techniques go hand-in-hand with more experimental approaches. Students need to be equally adept in silico, in vivo and in vitro.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;You are the founding Editor-in-Chief of PLOS Computational Biology, and you are enthusiastic about open science; open data and open education (like MOOCs and NIH training programs like Big Data to Knowledge). Can you explain why these matters are so important to you? Do you think non-scientist citizens should have equal access to scientific research and should actively participate?&lt;br&gt;
For instance, in Paris we had a data challenge (Epidemium) for cancer data, which involved engaging citizens to improve data management (databases) and data treatment. Do you think formal scientific education is necessary to participate in research?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Answer:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;The future of biomedical research involves a broader spectrum of data types and data which is publicly accessible. This creates unprecedented opportunities and we are already seeing the results. Examples are predicting healthcare outcomes from electronic health records either alone or in combination with other data. Use of mobility data to influence behavior etc. We need to foster the use of these data and the new methods emerging to use such open data. &lt;span class=&quot;highlightme&quot;&gt;Openness breaks down the traditional academic hierarchy and this is a good thing.&lt;/span&gt; We are doing what we can to foster new audiences to access and discover from the these data. The Open Science Prize and the Ideas labs we run with the NSF are examples.
&lt;blockquote&gt;While formal training is not necessary we must maintain the ethical standards and the rigor of the scientific method.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Do you think we are capable of coping with the amount of generated data? I have experienced in my own research that dealing even with medium size datasets can be problematic and many questions can be asked when looking for data from different angles. Is there a threat that with big data we could miss important questions? Some leaders of big data businesses say that we should slow the rate of data generation as data storage is costly and we are not able to analyse all these data. What’s your opinion?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Answer:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;This question is getting at data sustainability and maintenance and we have much work to do as a community here. We do not have a good handle on the rate of data generation, how to determine what to keep and what to discard, how to make the community aware of the persistence of particular types of data and many more issues. In the end we have to make decisions about cost vs benefit. In business the model is clearer — if we can leverage the data for the benefit of the company keep it, otherwise discard it. In academia there is a legacy of data preservation irrespective of perceived current value and the value cannot necessarily be measured in monetary terms. We need to develop metrics and best practices to define our data and subsequently make preservation decisions based upon these supporting data.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
 
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Today Big data, tomorrow…? What will be the next big step for health research?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Answer:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;The patient will become the center of the health care system as opposed to early health care (the physician) and today (the health care organization). The patient/participant will be empowered by a usable version of their own health record and the biomedical research which has used that record. They will interpret it themselves and whole new industries will appear to help them interpret the data and make decisions with the assistance of health care providers. Healthcare providers and healthcare industries will need to adjust to this new reality.
From a research perspective, systems based approaches will become more accepted and mainstream and be used as predictive tools Machine learning will figure more prominently.
Neuroscience will grow further as we explore the basis of consciousness and other aspects of the human condition. The relationship of health to the environment will be facilitated by the availability of large public environmental datasets and much more. Last but not least is the use of computational techniques and associated data in first response situations, notably concerning pandemics.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vision of data and healthcare outlined by Phil Bourne seem to be pretty optimistic. It is easy to see that the world of Data Science is complex but it is not lacking opportunities. This provides a lot of hope to researchers and students in the field of computational biology. As a community our mission is to seek opportunities in order to make the most of this universe; to explore it and to find new solutions for improving healthcare. Now is the ideal time to come forward with any ideas you have been sitting on — the potential benefits of data solutions are now more real than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;We extend our thanks to Phil Bourne for participating in this interview. Phil Bourne is a founding Editor-in-Chief of PLOS Computational Biology, which manages this collaborative blog.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;/strong&gt;Any views expressed are those of the author, not necessarily those of PLOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;footer&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on July 22, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/plos-comp-biol-field-reports-2016/data-and-the-future-of-healthcare-interview-with-phil-bourne-ismb16-db5ab9b296d4&quot;&gt;View the original&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
		   &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 
&lt;/html&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/interviewPhilBourne</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/interviewPhilBourne</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
        <category>conferenceISMB2016</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data Innovation</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;


&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body&gt;

     &lt;style&gt;


    iframe {display:block;margin:auto;}




      &lt;/style&gt;
 
      &lt;/body&gt;  
&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;i&gt;Where is &lt;strong&gt;data today&lt;/strong&gt;? Where will be &lt;strong&gt;data tomorrow&lt;/strong&gt; ? &lt;/i&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Hello... WHAT?&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://summit.hello-tomorrow.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hello Tomorrow Global Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is an international conference of trending technologies along with start-up competition fueling exchange between &lt;em&gt;research &amp; industry&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;capital &amp; innovators&lt;/em&gt;. It aims to support world-scale innovative solutions for global challenges.
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        Today, Hello Tomorrow is an interdisciplinary community with presence across 45 countries, gathering more than 15,000 innovators within the Hello Tomorrow ecosystem. The Hello Tomorrow Challenge, a global startup competition, has attracted nearly 5,000 startups across 112 countries since its inception in 2014.
        &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HT_Banner Twitter_CS6-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            As a &lt;strong&gt;PhD candidate equals &lt;i&gt;innovator&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; passionated about new technologies, especially &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;, I could not miss an opportunity to enjoy the show cast of the most exciting trends of tomorrow. Therefore, on the 13th &amp; 14th October at Centre 104 in Paris, I could listen, experience, network and taste the tomorrow. Here I will share with you my field report about &lt;strong&gt;Data Science&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://summit.hello-tomorrow.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hello Tomorrow Global Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HTGeneral.svg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://challenge.hello-tomorrow.org/HTChallenge2016-mediakit.zip&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source: Press kit Hello Tomorrow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Investor panel: AI &amp; data landscape&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        The panel assembled four experts investing into data universe, a mediator and employee of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cisco.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CISCO&lt;/a&gt; and a three venture capitalists : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/nathanbenaich&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nathan Benaich&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://playfaircapital.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Payfair capital&lt;/a&gt; in London, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/marieekeland&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Marie Ekeland&lt;/a&gt; : co-founder at &lt;a href=&quot;https://daphni.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Daphni&lt;/a&gt; and a fintech venture capitalist from &lt;a href=&quot;http://romuluscap.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Romulus capital&lt;/a&gt;.
        &lt;p&gt;First of all, they highlighted that data solutions and tools need to answer customer need, they need to be usable by the final user and adapted to its highly specified needs. It is not cool tech behind that will bring success to a data company. It is essential to understand usage and dynamics of the market, adding value to the whole chain&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Then asked about the &lt;strong&gt;team&lt;/strong&gt;, the key seems to finding qualified experts with complementary competences and match them with business trained fellows. Some start-up tend to be evaluated on the base of number of &lt;strong&gt;PhD graduated members&lt;/strong&gt;, even though PhDs are without doubts an added value, it is not wise to estimate team value based only on this criterion&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;They also shared a few tips &lt;strong&gt;how to enter the industry&lt;/strong&gt;. Again, it seems that answering the demand and carefully listening to the customer is the key. To &lt;strong&gt;start off&lt;/strong&gt; and get data, it was advised to negotiate with a customer or find a partner collecting data, simulating data can be also an option.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/nathanbenaich&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nathan Benaich&lt;/a&gt; highlights also that there are &lt;i&gt;simple&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;complex&lt;/i&gt; cases, where with simple cases can be as much as 80% of total but the the complex ones may take same efforts or they would need to be treated individually. She referred to policy making such as visa applications for instance where immigrant from countries with clear situation could be classified and processed very easily, while immigrants for regions touched by was would need special assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deep learning&lt;/strong&gt; was of course mentioned as one of trending technologies for voice, image and video processing, that gained value coupled with &lt;strong&gt;Big Data&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;IoT&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;AI&lt;/strong&gt;. However, this recent advances does not affect all fields of AI and still there is lots of room for progress.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;Asked about &lt;strong&gt;advice for early stage entrepreneurs&lt;/strong&gt; they admitted they do not like giving advice for free.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;But finally they revealed three tips
            &lt;ul&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;identify big issues and build a team, go big and attract right investor&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;find your path, build step by step&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;run your data buiness now, it is right place and right time &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;Panel: Responsability of AI&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HTPanel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In this session experts : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/sean-o-heigeartaigh-03b33b29&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Dr Seán Ó hÉigeartaigh&lt;/a&gt; the the Executive Director of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.csap.cam.ac.uk/network/sean-oheigeartaigh/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the Centre for the Study of Existential Risk&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Cambridge, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/rodolphe-gelin-b565271&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Rodolphe Gelin&lt;/a&gt; EVP Chief Scientific Officer at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/company/98040?trk=prof-0-ovw-prev_pos&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Aldebaran Robotics - Softbank Group&lt;/a&gt;  discussed possible ethical risks that can be raised by AI. &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Nowadays, systems transforms from rule-based programmable computer machines into Artificial Intelligence that can adapt and learn by itself from the provided data. Firstly, it is worth to ask the question what actually is AI (if you are interested by this subject check also &lt;a href=&quot;http://spectrum.ieee.org/automaton/robotics/artificial-intelligence/why-alphago-is-not-ai&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Why AlphaGo Is Not AI&lt;/a&gt;).
            &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Definition of Artificial intelligence keeps changing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
            Along with an algorithm there is a question of the &lt;i&gt;body&lt;/i&gt; that will incorporate the intelligence. Also how to translate abstract thinking into computer thinking.
        &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;There is a significant progress in speech recognition. Robots can understand human language, interpret it and answer in the same terms. It also impacts significantly healthcare where data is screening for drugs side effects.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;For sure, future will bring even more progress and, according to Seán and Rodolphe, will pose serious ethical issues in 2030s This is why, a &lt;em&gt;deep reflexion about the future is necessary now&lt;/em&gt;. The society should be prepared for the AI that will probable exceed our expectations and impact us more than we can imagine.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Right now, technology is dependent on the design but also on the users. Just like in a movie &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3531824/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nerve&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; recently in theaters, an innocent game can become dreadful if the users make it so. Thus, technology even today is not free from ethical dimension.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In Rodolphe&#39;s opinion, robots will become more and more independent. They will be trained on the data we provide, to they can reflected numerous biases, i.e. they can be resist. Therefore, there must be defined legal constrains on who is responsible for the robot and its acts. Answer to many ethical questions are not clear and depends a lot on the culture and society. An example of it is &lt;i&gt;the trolley problem&lt;/i&gt; that &lt;i&gt;Google&#39;s self driving car project&lt;/i&gt; asked to consumers. The problem consist of moral dilemma: should some people be sacrificed to save others and which ones (to read more about it read in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/innovations/wp/2015/12/01/googles-leader-on-self-driving-cars-downplays-the-trolley-problem/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Washington Post&lt;/a&gt;). If you want to experience the moral choices play this &lt;a href=&quot;http://moralmachine.mit.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;game &quot;Moral Machine&quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; designed by MIT. &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;Therefore &lt;em&gt;AI ethics&lt;/em&gt; is more about &lt;em&gt;designing morality&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ethical codes implemented in machines should be consulted with the people that will interact with given robots. Education and widely accessible information is the start to make society aware that some decision taking on moral codes will be necessary. There are places, like for instance in elderly care, where robots are more than welcome to interact with people. This is because the robot will not judge, will not mock. The robot will professionally assist and elder person to the toilet or take it down the stairs. Also in the case of war, killer robots would replace humans going to dangerous zones, which already happens a lot with drones (to read more about pros and cons of AI weapons &lt;a href=&quot;http://spectrum.ieee.org/automaton/robotics/military-robots/why-should-we-ban-autonomous-weapons-to-survive&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://spectrum.ieee.org/automaton/robotics/artificial-intelligence/we-should-not-ban-killer-robots&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In general society fears novelty, it constitutes a break for the progress, but this a part of the process.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Asked about hat will be &lt;strong&gt;the next hot topic around AI&lt;/strong&gt;. Seán answered it will be about algorithm fairness and systems that will be able to explain their logics to human. Rodolphe added that we should conceive machines that will share with us their observations and this would improve our human traditional way of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;There is no doubt intelligent designs raise ethical challenges that will need to be faced by system designers, companies, society and governments. The white house released recently a report: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/whitehouse_files/microsites/ostp/NSTC/preparing_for_the_future_of_ai.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preparing the future of AI.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It is wise to think now about challenges of tomorrow, at least before it is too late...&lt;/p&gt;

 
&lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Keynotes&lt;/h3&gt;
 &lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can watch entire day on YouTube if you click at this &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/KXhbBLg4WDE?t=16224&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Hacking &amp; security&lt;/h4&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HTsecurity.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheKenMunroShow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ken Munro&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pentestpartners.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Pen Test Parntners&lt;/a&gt;, company based in UK, specialized in hacking security systems in order to help companies find defaults in their software. He presented a few study cases of cars. In one case, there was a possibility to unlock the car though cracking the password to the app of the car. In the second case, the car software had hidden options that allowed the hacker to manipulate the vehicle. And this examples are just a drop in the see of possibilities of hacking electronic, smart devices. Most of users are not aware the systems can have security holes, they trust the company. While the companies have often an interest in hiding the fact that their devices can be hacked. An beneficial approach would be more wide spread interventions of companies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pentestpartners.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Pen Test Partners&lt;/a&gt; in order to assure the safety of software we use, especially like as in case of autonomous cars, human life can be at stake. 
 &lt;/p&gt;

               
&lt;h4&gt;Achieving Super Vision&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HT_keynoteVR.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/raymond-lo-58852a92&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Raymond Lo&lt;/a&gt;, CTO of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.metavision.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Meta Co.&lt;/a&gt; made a live demo of his Augmented Vision device that allows to manipulate virtual objects in real time. The product can be pre-ordered now for $949.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TyXePLD54uU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
        &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            The augmented reality can find its application in brain and behavioral research, in business, in communication, in education, in online shopping, in computer games and in everyday life. (And it is cool!).
        &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The company is looking for innovation, so if you have ideas how to improve their product contact Raymond!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;CARDIOLOGS: Machine Learning for healthcare &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HT_keynoteCardio.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;During an afternoon dedicated to AI &amp; Computing, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/yann-fleureau-b1179983&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yann Fleureau&lt;/a&gt; CEO of &lt;a href=&quot;https://cardiologs.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CARDIOLOGS&lt;/a&gt; presented how &lt;strong&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/strong&gt; can help doctors to better diagnose cardiovascular diseases. Cardiologs technology is based on &lt;strong&gt;deep learning &amp; image recognition&lt;/strong&gt;. It is supposed to detect and highlight possible anomalies in electrocardiogram outputs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/yann-fleureau-b1179983&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yann Fleureau&lt;/a&gt; highlighted that their product is not designed to replace doctors but to facilitate their work and help to save time. 
    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Building game changing data sets&lt;/h4&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HT_keynoteDeeploop.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
   
    The last Keynote in AI &amp; Computing session was given by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/augustindeepomatic&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Augustin Marty&lt;/a&gt; CEO of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deepomatic.com/#/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Deepomatic&lt;/a&gt;. The company proposes solutions for better and more adapted data science solutions. First, to advance &lt;strong&gt;deep learning&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deepomatic.com/#/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Deepomatic&lt;/a&gt; proposes a service to speed up and enhance library building that itelf uses machine learning to facilitate the tedious task of object selection and labeling (inception!).   &lt;/p&gt;    &lt;blockquote&gt; Deep Learning recipe: deep learning framework + annotated images + annotators &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HT_keynoteDeep.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;p&gt;It takes in average 10 min to annotate one image, and you need a good library to make your algorithm efficient, and for robotics it can take more than one hour to describe the environment. Creating datasets became real bottleneck of deep learning.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt;AI is for everyone because algorithm and computing power are becoming a commodities so a bottleneck now is creating a good dataset. [Augustin Marty]&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is a need to industrialize annotation process &amp; democratize dataset production. The key is to have dedicated software. &lt;strong&gt;Active learning&lt;/strong&gt; allows to build deep learning system with the minimal necessary number of images. It can reduce time of annotation from 70 to 10 min.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Presented solutions look impressive, it would be interesting to get some user experience and find out if all type of objects can be annotated easier with help of active learning.&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;h3&gt;Start-up challenge winners&lt;/h3&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;In the category of Data &amp; AI the start-up winning the prize of €15,000 were &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.koniku.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Koniku&lt;/a&gt;. The company produces drones based on biological neuronal circuits. &lt;blockquote&gt;The hybrid chipset known as the koniku kore provides a small footprint, low energy, sensory intelligent solution to address complex problems. [KONIKU]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/startup.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
     &lt;h3&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h3&gt;

     &lt;p&gt;In overall, &lt;strong&gt;Hello Tomorrow Global Summit&lt;/strong&gt; was great adventure. Gathering motivated people, cutting-edge technology and capital in the same place is a remarkable achievement. There is no doubts there is a lot to happen in Data Universe in upcoming years and data is present now in many industries. What is more, data is a rich topic in itself and can take different flavors combined with AI, IoT or ethics. We will for sure surprised about its potential and new technologies born from this industry.&lt;/p&gt;
       
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  
&lt;/section&gt;

&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/HelloT/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/HelloT/</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Intro and retrospective on Computational Biology &amp; Data</title>
        <description>&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body&gt;
    &lt;style&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; body {
        background-color: blue;
    }
    
    .highlightme {
        background-color: #ccffe5;
    }
    
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/style&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;b&gt;Data, big data, omics data, noisy data, a lack of data, data overflow, open data.&lt;/b&gt;Data is an increasingly critical part of life as a researcher — particularly in the field of computational biology. How to treat data? How to manage data? How to smartly produce data? How to simulate data? How to reproduce data? Data, data, data…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But what is &lt;b&gt;Computational Biology&lt;/b&gt;? In the past, it was seen as a support for biological research; a set of tools helping answer biological questions asked by researchers — real researchers that is. However, when you consider recent breakthroughs, dynamical development of this discipline and the impact it has, it is easy to see why those in the field believe that that computational biology is and will be a driving force of biological research. What is particularly striking is the change in computational biology from &lt;b&gt;descriptive to data-driven science&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_Fotor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It all started with genomics. When biologist trained in wet-lab work they could not treat their data themselves and this is how new discipline was born. Like all young disciplines, it had to negotiate its place in the research landscape. Today, computational biology is still expanding thanks to new technologies and the ongoing digital revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Breakthroughs&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An undeniable innovator of computational biology, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iscb.org/ismb2016program/keynotes/batzoglou&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Serafim Batzoglou&lt;/a&gt;, in his keynote talk at ISMB 2016, presented his vision of the past and the future of this discipline. His talk started with human genome sequencing, through to data manipulation, to personal genomics and finally artificial intelligence. He stated research need to keep up with new technologies with a quote from the TV series
        &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2575988/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“I don’t want to live in a world where someone else is making the world a better place better than me”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In his talk, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iscb.org/ismb2016program/keynotes/batzoglou&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Serafim Batzoglou&lt;/a&gt; made the somewhat controversial comment that &lt;span class=&quot;highlightme&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;AI will replace medical doctors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; in near future and he named his candidate for most important and promising technology: &lt;b&gt;deep learning&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_learning&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Deep learning&lt;/a&gt; is a branch of machine learning based on a set of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algorithm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt; that attempt to model high-level abstractions in data by using a deep graph with multiple processing layer; composed of multiple linear and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_transformation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;non-linear transformations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/keynotetalk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Single-cell transcriptomics&lt;/b&gt; were unofficially named most exciting technology for studying biological systems - with three out of six keynote speakers talking about their recent progress when treating single cell transcriptomics data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iscb.org/ismb2016program/keynotes/batzoglou&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Serafim Batzoglou&lt;/a&gt; also mentioned clustering algorithm, called SimlR challenging existing methods of dimension reduction . The &lt;a href=&quot;http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/05/09/052225&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt; of the article is accessible at &lt;a href=&quot;http://biorxiv.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://biorxiv.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;figure&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/simlR.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Outline of SIMLR from “Visualization and analysis of single-cell RNA-seq data by kernelbased similarity learning” — Image credit: Bo Wang et al ,2016 , (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
        &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iscb.org/ismb2016program/keynotes/dudoit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sandrine Dudoit&lt;/a&gt; also referred to single-cell data; with particular attention to treating the problem of noise to signal ratio and data reproducibility. In her lab more robust tools of clustering are under development. For example: &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/epurdom/clusterExperiment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;clusterExperiment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; decides on clusters based on many clustering methods and picks the ones that are the most stable.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The keynote talk by Sarah Teichmann showcased a cutting-edge example of exploration of single-cell data. In publication she co-authors (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26950746&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“Tcell fate and clonality inference from single-cell transcriptomes”&lt;/a&gt;), full-length paired T-cell receptor (TCR) sequences are reconstructed from single cell data.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A key trend currently is to gather information at the highest level of accuracy and then group it into meaningful blocks of knowledge which best characterize the data and correspond to biological reality, or even better, discover unknown pieces of biological systems. This is how computational biology is driving biological research today.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And there will be more; more data, more challenges, more breathtaking discoveries!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coud_Fotor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One them is &lt;b&gt;education&lt;/b&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Bourne&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phil Bourne&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nih.gov/news/health/dec2013/od-09.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Associate Director for Data Science of NIH&lt;/a&gt;, in the workshop &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Education in Bioinformatics — Exploiting Cloud and Virtual Resources for Training&lt;/a&gt;, highlighted the importance of &lt;b&gt;cloud data&lt;/b&gt; training to keep the pace of technologies developed by companies (e.g. Amazon, Google, iPlant). The new generation of computational biologists and Bioinformaticians, as well as senior researchers, require solid and up-to-date training. This is why the NIH proposes numerous programs facilitating cloud training. Unfortunately, it is not the case at all research institutes currently, but it definitely should be in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another important issue raised by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Bourne&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phil Bourne&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iscb.org/ismb2016program/keynotes/batzoglou&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Serafim Batzoglou&lt;/a&gt; was the importance of keeping data open. Phil mentioned in particular the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/articles/sdata201618&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;FAIR Data Principles&lt;/a&gt; which stand for:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability, and Reusability&lt;/strong&gt; - These serve to guide data producers and publishers as they navigate around obstacles, thereby helping to maximize the added-value gained by contemporary, scholarly publishing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iscb.org/ismb2016program/keynotes/batzoglou&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Serafim Batzoglou&lt;/a&gt; outlined the necessity of making data public in one of the slides in his keynote talk (quoted):&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;Biggest obstacle: wide, free data availability&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;Ideal&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Millions of publicity available genomes, medical records, phenotypes, enivornments&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Far reaching anti data-based discrimination laws; GINA great start&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;Not ideal&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Data silos in hospitals, health care providers, gov’t, direct-to-direct consumer companies&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Specialized large-scale projects (1000 genomes but no phenotypes/medical records)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;What about privacy?&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;No cancer patients have died yet because of data privacy breach&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;My Facebook page reveals much more private stuff about me than my genome or medical record&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;highlightme&quot;&gt;Let’s make our data public — if 5% of us do, probably enough to make a big difference.
Let’s do it without waiting for legislation!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
  

    &lt;hr /&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Flaws&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are still some flaws with regards to big data — but it still represents big hope for computational biology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/urilaserson&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Uri Laserson&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cloudera.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cloudera&lt;/a&gt; (a leader platform for data management and analysis), &lt;a href=&quot;http://fr.slideshare.net/urilaserson/genomics-is-not-special-towards-data-intensive-biology&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“Genomic is not special”&lt;/a&gt;. He expressed the view that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;Computational biologists are reinventing the wheel for big data biology analysis&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even though the statement is bold, there is some truth in it. It looks like industrial solutions for big data somehow outperform research solutions. This is why &lt;b&gt;more collaboration between research and industry is needed&lt;/b&gt; to fill the gap. On the other hand, this collaboration cannot happen at the price of data ownership. Academy needs to find a solution to attract world-scale talents that right now goes where big data is linked tightly to big money.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another recurrent problem for many computational biologists and bioinformaticians is their place in biological research. Despite an improving amount of recognition of computational work in wet labs, there is still a number of places that lack of expertise in data analysis. Old analysis methods are reproduced and consequently spread used by others in the field — all because a number of researchers are using them.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Programming or statistical input is not acknowledged enough and this is where there can some friction between experimentalists and theoreticians that can hinder progress. Strolling through alleys of the poster hall at ISMB 2016, overheard many accounts of interactions between wet and dry lab. Most of them recalled tension, disappointment or misunderstanding. This is why &lt;b&gt;education is really crucial&lt;/b&gt;. No one cannot be an expert in all domains, but a comprehensible overview of each other worlds, common vocabulary and goals are essential to building a common future.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;hr /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Computational biology is in the heart of digital revolution.&lt;/b&gt; Paradoxically a lack and an excess of data make this discipline extremely intriguing and challenging. With individual countries frequently making decisions on policies that have an impact on the direction and pace of the development of solutions, data’s impact on our future is undeniable. &lt;b&gt;But then again, what is data? A set of numbers?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;From technical point of view, each of us is a multidimensional data-set. Can we be easily reduced to a few dimensions? Can our time dimension be predicted from real time data? Can someone own us? Are we approaching era of digital slavery?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hole_Fotor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You may be also interested in :&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://compbiofieldreports.plos.org/computational-biology-moving-into-the-future-one-click-at-a-time-83f81c0e293d#.qy67d53p8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Computational Biology: Moving into the Future One Click at a Time. Message from ISCB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;/strong&gt;Any views expressed are those of the author, not necessarily those of PLOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;footer&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on Setpember 13, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/plos-comp-biol-field-reports-2016/computational-biology-data-ismb16-1607154654ea#.ijpvjgnnw&quot;&gt;View the original&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/compbiodata</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/compbiodata</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
        <category>conferenceISMB2016</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Career transition - from academia to industry</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
	&lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;

&lt;/head&gt;

 &lt;body&gt;

     &lt;style&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;    	
        
		body { background-color:blue; }
		.highlightme { background-color:#ccffe5; }
 &lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;/style&gt;
 
      &lt;/body&gt;  
&lt;section&gt;
	&lt;h3&gt;Ph. D. and what after? Do you know?&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For most of us, a natural choice after completing a science masters is a research career. The path is clear: a Ph.D., followed perhaps by an international postdoc and then a faculty position, and you become a PI or a Professor. However, some of us (including me) at different stages of this long path are asking ourselves a question: &lt;strong&gt;do I really fit here?&lt;/strong&gt; At this point, some people may choose to abandon research for non-research work they may find more fulfilling, better-paid, more entertaining or less stressful. These people may make the transition into science liaison, editor, consultant or project manager positions. Others may find happiness in continuing with research, &lt;strong&gt;but in industry setting.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;From two &lt;i&gt;Birds of Flight&lt;/i&gt; sessions: Student Council Career Central and Navigating the Industry Career Path at ISMB 2016, I have  compiled various testimonies about doing research in industry and some tips for applicants seeking out those positions.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/carrer_un1_Fotor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;In brief, the difference between industry and academia is :&lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Academia&lt;/strong&gt;: how can I generate new informantion that will improve world knowledge? Personal career is often ahead of the main goal. &lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry&lt;/strong&gt;: There is a specific problem we need to try to solve as quickly as we can working as a team&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;h3&gt;Main differences between working in industry and in academia:&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;ol&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;faster peace — This can be a plus (stimulating) or a minus (stressful) depending on your working style or personal preference.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;real deadlines — A lot of money can be invested in projects you are part of and so there is pressure to achieve goals or abandon projects where necessary&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;constructive feedback — For example, at the end of the year the &lt;i&gt;Amyris&lt;/i&gt; company gives employees &lt;strong&gt;feedback&lt;/strong&gt; on different competences. This is based on what is collected from their co-workers and project leaders, and can include evaluations on communication (written and oral), individual performance , performance in the team, leadership skills, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;improve your skills with the aid of the company- i.e. Your oral presentation may be recorded and commented in detail to help you overcome your weak points&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;your manager is not a PI - Your relationships within the working environment will therefore be different&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;less competition, more &lt;strong&gt;collaboration&lt;/strong&gt; between research groups within the company&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;working hours — Within industry employees can be expensive: you need to learn to be very efficient during your allocated working hours&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;put aside your ego —  Being capable of working well within a team is crucial, &lt;strong&gt;no one wants to work with a super-star&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;you don’t need to raise &lt;strong&gt;money&lt;/strong&gt; — there is typically a whole department that takes care of this, you are free to focus on research&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;less &lt;strong&gt;freedom&lt;/strong&gt; on your research and goals - as the topic of your research and goals are typically led by the company&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;you may still be able to publish research, but it is not a high priority like in Academia - Lawyers may decide what you can actually make public&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;you can and you should still network with researchers - Probably your ex-fellows&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;you can collaborate with academic labs&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;your creation belongs to the company — No fights to have your name on the paper, but on the other hand, you do not get credit in the traditional sense&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;your work and the company can be motivated by money&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ol&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/career_un_5_Fotor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;h3&gt;Some tips for the job search and interview process&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;h4 &gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#999999&quot;&gt;Key tips&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		&lt;i&gt;Team work, team work, team work.&lt;/i&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Industry is probably not suited to individuals who would prefer to work alone.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		According to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:nicole.bodycombe@pfizer.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nicole Bodycombe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/href&gt;, technical skills are not the most important point of your dossier because she argues that everyone can be trained. What is much more important is the ability to &lt;strong&gt;communicate&lt;/strong&gt; with coworkers and community and also &lt;strong&gt;problem solve&lt;/strong&gt;.
	&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;h4&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#999999&quot;&gt;Interview process&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Different stages can be applied: CV screening — make sure it stands out for example including recommendation letter from some in the company, phone screening, group lunch (evaluate your social skills), pairing, a task/ exercise / problem to solve (result is not the most important the process of searching for an answer is)&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do your homework&lt;/strong&gt; before the interview: see products, related publications, try to get in contact with someone in the company through your network to learn about company habits, goals and ambiance.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Use interview to &lt;strong&gt;learn more about the company&lt;/strong&gt;. What is the working environment like? What kind of vocabulary do they use? Always ask questions!&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;You can read testimonies from applicants who have interviewed for different companies online in websites as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glassdoor.fr&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.glassdoor.fr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;h4&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#999999&quot;&gt;Your role in the industry&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
			For a computational biologist different roles are possible: data analyst, software engineer (producing tools), project-shaping. Along with many others! Sometimes you can negotiate with the company about your role, but try to flexible and open into new opportunities.

		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;h4&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#999999&quot;&gt;How to network?&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
			Most of people you know may stay in academia. It is likely that your PI will be able to offer you more advice on continuing your career is academia than they would be able to about pursuing one in industry. &lt;strong&gt;So how can you meet people from the big world outside of academia?&lt;/strong&gt; Look among your colleagues, it is likely that there is someone who has at least collaborated with industry partners. You can also use Linkedin to find more people working within industry. Reach out to people and go to local meet ups. &lt;strong&gt;Be curious and proactive&lt;/strong&gt;.
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;h4&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#999999&quot;&gt;PostDoc or not?&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
			For those who are debating between getting more experience in research before transitioning into industry or moving straight across, the answer is: &lt;strong&gt;it depends&lt;/strong&gt;. For more skill based positions like data analysts or developers it is not necessary to have an extensive research background. However if you wish to lead a research group in industry it can be an asset to have progressed further in academia.
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;highlightme&quot;&gt;Important remark: If you are &lt;strong&gt;not U.S. resident&lt;/strong&gt; looking to land an industry job in U.S., it may be better for you to do a postdoc first for practical reasons. Getting a working visa from a distance can be a long and difficult process and having a research position can make it easier.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
		&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;h4&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#999999&quot;&gt;What if I want to go back to academia?&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Well, it may be challenging but certainly not impossible. Prof. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/r/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.linkedin.com%2Fin%2Fjudithblake&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Judith Blake&lt;/a&gt; made it. The key is to keep contact with academiaby attending conferences and keeping up to date with new research. However, it may be more challenging to obtain positions that look at your impact factor.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;To sum up, in order to succeed in securing jobs in academia, (according to our experts) you should do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;be open to opportunities and enjoy yourself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/carrer_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;figcaption&gt;From left to right: Nicole Bodycombe, Blake Borgeson, Lan Hu, Scott Markel&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;The experts that contributed the testimonials that make up the basis for this post were: Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/amoolyasingh&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Amoolya Singh&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://amyris.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Amyrisc Inc&lt;/a&gt;), Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/sarah-teichmann-9975646b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sarah Teichmann&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebi.ac.uk/research/teichmann&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Group Leader at EBI&lt;/a&gt;), Prof. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/judithblake&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Judith Blake&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jax.org/research-and-faculty/faculty/judy-blake&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jaxon Laboratories&lt;/a&gt;, previous: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.si.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Smithsonian Institution&lt;/a&gt;), Mrs. &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:nicole.bodycombe@pfizer.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nicole Bodycombe&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pfizer.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pfizer&lt;/a&gt;), Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blake.borgeson@recursionpharma.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Blake Borgeson&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recursionpharma.com/team.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RECURSION Pharmaceuticals&lt;/a&gt;), Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:hulan0@gmail.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lan Hu&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bio-rad.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bio-Rad Laboratories&lt;/a&gt;)and Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Scott.MARKEL@3ds.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Scott Markel&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://accelrys.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BIOVIA&lt;/a&gt;). All of the above (except Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/sarah-teichmann-9975646b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sarah Teichmann&lt;/a&gt;) were or are working an industry setting with research being a key component of what they do.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Some of them chose to leave academia because of personal situations, working hours (industry jobs can sometimes be less time-consuming) or in an effort to have a better work-life balance. Their testimonies highlight that there are many varied and exciting opportunities within industry.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;

	&lt;h4&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h4&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personally, as I strongly consider working in industry later on in my life.&lt;/strong&gt;Even though these testimonies are somewhat limited in the sense that this is only a snapshot of some people’s experience, they give an idea about the industry sector’s expectations and the benefits of working there.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Sadly there is no magic recipe for choosing between academia and industry. &lt;strong&gt;Finding the right job is like buying shoes.&lt;/strong&gt; Some are exactly the right fit and some you may need to adjust a bit. The key is to try as many as possible and to be well-prepared. Thanks to an increasing number of career development sessions at scientific conferences, more people will be able to explore their options and contribute to research in the best way they can — be that working in academia or in industry.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I wish you all best of luck with your career!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/carrer_un_4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;/strong&gt;Any views expressed are those of the author, not necessarily those of PLOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;footer&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on July 22, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/plos-comp-biol-field-reports-2016/research-in-an-industry-setting-testimonials-from-ismb16-3d3de62ab260#.rsmuquy2c&quot;&gt;View the original&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
		   &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 
&lt;/html&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/academiatoindustry</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/academiatoindustry</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
        <category>conferenceISMB2016</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Student Council Symposium at Orlando</title>
        <description>&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;

&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Student Council Symposium at Orlando #SCSOrlando2016&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started off ISMB2016 by attending the Student Council Symposium. This meeting is dedicated to students, post docs, and young researchers in the fields of Computational Biology and Bioinformatics and it gave me a chance to present my work with an oral presentation and a poster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The day started with an Ice Breaking event:&lt;strong&gt; Scientific speed dating. &lt;/strong&gt;We were given a few minutes to get introduced to other person present in the room. Despite myself (and many others) being massively jet-lagged, it was quite entertaining and it gave us the impression that you were continuing the day with friends, instead of strangers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/jq_Fotor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;First keynote speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: John Quackenbush, professor of Computational Biology and Biology and Bioinformatics, talked to us about some of his main research lines these days entitled &lt;em&gt;Networks from gentoype to phenotype.&lt;/em&gt; The main highlight of his talk was his network-based analysis coupled with transcriptomic and mutation data. He introduced an approach where he constructed networks specific to patients and then he compared their structure described in “&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1505.06440&quot; data-href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1505.06440&quot; class=&quot;markup--anchor markup--p-anchor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Estimating sample-specific regulatory networks&lt;/a&gt;”. He then criticized some of classical approaches calling them a ‘bio-poetry’. He also gave us quick overview of his approach to SNPs and eQTLs. He then went on to describe how important interdisciplinarity when working in computational biology is, using the example of implementing matrix formulation from quantum physics to describe network transitions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were &lt;strong&gt;15 students presenting&lt;/strong&gt; for 15minutes each. This years most represented topics were protein structure reconstruction and sequence analysis. Some students shared their reflection on being in between two disciplines: biology &amp;amp; computer science. I personally found all talks very well prepared, most of speakers were clear and interesting. The participants came from different countries all around the world and some, like me, made it thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://symposium.iscbsc.org/tf-announcement&quot; data-href=&quot;http://symposium.iscbsc.org/tf-announcement&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ISCB travel fellowship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/jt_Fotor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;The second keynote&lt;/strong&gt; talk was given by Janet Thornton. She is Director Emeritus of EMBL-EBI and Senior Scientist, with scientific interest in protein structure. She not only shared with us an overview of her career path and research, but also personal reflections on different steps of her life: student, post-doc, PI. She left us with lots of very useful tips. She is a very warm and humble person and is a great example for many researchers. She expressed her belief that computational biology is an expanding field and that this will create job opportunities for young researchers. She was very passionate and happy about her unexpected career path she made from physics to computational biology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/advice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elsevier, the sponsor of SCS, prepared also for us a special demo of their new product &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elsevier.com/solutions/pathway-studio-biological-research&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pathway Studio&lt;/a&gt; and offered us a free trial! They were very patient guiding us through their step-by-step tutorial and answering numerous questions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Symposium ended with a &lt;strong&gt;poster session &lt;/strong&gt;which was accompanied with some snacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Participants then voted for the best poster and talk. The winners are to announced on Monday during ISCB Town Hall (!!!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We were also invited to closing &lt;strong&gt;social event&lt;/strong&gt; when we could talk to our peers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SCS was for me a great start to my trip. It was great to see other passionate students and discuss engaging research topics. Hope to cross paths with them again over the course of the main ISMB conference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the SCS, I still had some time to explore the Swan &amp;amp; Dolphin hotel area. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hote.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;hr&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;/strong&gt;Any views expressed are those of the author, not necessarily those of PLOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;footer&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on July 11, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/bba71aad7353&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;View the original&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;

&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 
&lt;/section&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/scs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/scs</guid>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
        <category>conferenceISMB2016</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Learning business at Sorbonne</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;

&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;i&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy, Finance and Marketing.&lt;/strong&gt; Why should I care about them if I am a Ph. D. student? Leave stereotypes behind and find out.&lt;/i&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;What is CBA?&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        Certificate in Business and Administration is a course organized by &lt;a href=&quot;http://cfdip.uspc.fr/fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CFDiP&lt;/a&gt; for students of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sorbonne-paris-cite.fr/en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Université Sorbonne Paris Cité&lt;/a&gt;. It has been inspired by best American Universities that propose CBA for their graduate students. It is happening in two steps of 7 and 5 days separated by 6 months. Entirely in English, CBA targets motivated Ph. D. students from different fields that are interested in pursuing their career outside of academia. It fills the gap in the current educational system that not prepare STEM students to land jobs in private sector. The program not only gives an overview of how company and business works. But, even more importantly gives an on-hand experience in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.capsim.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Capsim Business Simulator&lt;/a&gt; as it is done in top Business Schools. Here is a snapshot of the first week of the CBA challenge. Check also  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?src=typd&amp;q=%23CBAsorbonne&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;#CBASorbonne&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PxGirard&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@px.girard&lt;/a&gt;. 
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/strategy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
        Why companies pay consultants? What make a company grow and develop and other go bankrupt in the same environment? These were questions our teacher and the course coordinator &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:px.girard@gmail.com&quot;&gt;Pierre Girard&lt;/a&gt; addressed in his lecture about strategy. We learned how to analyze environment through PESTEL on a real-life study cases. We were also introduced also to ethics and the life cycle of companies. This gave us a general overview of what external factors weight most for company success and what matters we can face one working in or running a firm.
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Finance&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/finance.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        Second day was scarified to financial matters. Jiri Tresl explained us the difference between accounting and finance where the first one is the module providing information and the second taking decision and thus they both are inseparable to run a company. 
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Finance is an art of money management&lt;/blockquote&gt;
        We have been introduced to the whole new vocabulary: assets, investments, cash, liability, equity, shares, stocks, bonds and debts. We learned basic rules determining these alien world. Since  then we will all remember that 
                &lt;blockquote&gt;profit does NOT equal cash&lt;/blockquote&gt;
        This class really served us to understand how to manage finance of our virtual company in CAPSIM&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt;!

    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Marketing&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CCosine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Finally &#39;the key to business success&#39; - marketing. With dynamic Christine Coisne we went trough tactics and concepts. We studied evolution of company LEGO what is the difference between Transactional  and relational marketing, how to perform SWOT analysis and targets differentiation. Now for sure, we will not take &#39;marketing mix&#39; for a name of a drink and we will not think Maslow was a pharaoh of ancient Egypt. 
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;They made it!&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Meeting people that made career transition&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;Maureen Alivon&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She has a bachelor in biology and master in pharmacology. She worked in a lab of Hôpital Européen Georges Pompidou about the effects of antiangiogenic drugs on large arteries elastic properties and she got the CBA certificate during her Ph.D. And after her Ph. D. she was asking herself a question what to do. She decided to look for a job outside of academia. However it was not easy. She has sent lots of CV. She event went though interview process to hear she cannot work in marketing because she has no experience. A situation we probably hear about. Finally, 3 months after her Ph. D. defense she got recommended for Medical Communication Manager in Servier. And she enjoys her job a lot. She shared with us some tips answered generously our questions. At first place, she highlighted that Ph. D. is a big thing and everything we will learn about time and work management will be useful in our future job. She advised not to wait for engage career transition. Faster the better, in order to build our professional network. She admitted she was not good with social media and not engaged in associative activities but it can definitely help to get a job. Even though she is not continuing on making experiments and she cannot publish, she highly appreciate her actual position and she is climbing up on the corporate ladder becoming project manager in upcoming month. 
    &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;Noemie Ballot&lt;/h4&gt; 
                &lt;p&gt;She is now a manager of European Project Green Nano Films and in parallel works for a start-up. She told us her way from Ph.D. in Material Chemistry to project management. She found her job thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.intelliagence.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ABG L&#39;intelli&#39;agence&lt;/a&gt;. She said the CBA experience gave her curiosity to learn more about management, leadership, teamwork, finance budget and helped her to practice English. As Maureen she highlighted importance of building a professional network early in the career. She said we need to talk about our job search to everyone around, use social media. She encouraged us to just talk about what we do with passion and project ourselves in different jobs with our motivation and skills, to be confident and open-minded. She listed for us some possible jobs after Ph.D.:
                
                        &lt;ul&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;R&amp;D&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;research in companies&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;science monitoring&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;patents&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;leadership consulting&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;research projects management&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;science communication&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;scientific editor&lt;/li&gt;

                        &lt;/ul&gt;

                    She shared also some platforms we can look for job:
                &lt;ul&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.intelliagence.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ABG L&#39;intelli&#39;agence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apec.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;APEC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Linekdin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fr.viadeo.com/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Viadeo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cadremploi.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cadremploi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/naturejobs/science/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Naturejobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                        

                        &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;Nesrine Benyahia&lt;/h4&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;
                Our last guest Nesrine is still a Ph. D. student in health law while working for a start up  - consulting firm &lt;a href=&quot;http://bmcconsultingfrance.wix.com/bmcconsulting&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BMC Consulting&lt;/a&gt; she founded together  with two friends with law and business backgrounds. We asked her how she manages to carry on her Ph. D. and work at the same time. She confirmed it is not easy to have several tasks and that she works everywhere, in the metro, on weekends etc. but it is worth the hassle. 
            &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;CAPSIM&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; Business Simulation&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        The most exciting part of the course was a competition in CAPSIM&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; business simulator. For 4 days, six teams of 5-6 members managing each a B2B company producing sensors. There are five main sectors and each team starts with one product in one sector: High End, Low End, Traditional, Size and Performance. We had to manage R&amp;D, Marketing, Production and Finance. The competition was on for 6 rounds I was in Digby team with 4 great fellows: Clara, Rawan, Charlotte and Nirmal. I will share with you some of our strategy
        &lt;br&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Round 0&lt;/strong&gt; 
        &lt;br&gt;
        In the round 0 we had a chance to learn how to use the simulation and test some strategies. We decided to create a new product in High End as the age was the most important criterion for this sector. To estimate how much money we need to borrow and how many units we need produce we made positive and negatives estimations. We quickly realized that releasing new product is really costly and doesn&#39;t bring returns for at least 2 rounds. On the top it makes impossible to improve other products because R&amp;D works on the new products. We also took too much debt and we sold out on some products. We have seen also powerful impact of marketing where a similar product would sold much better if its awareness and accessibility were high. We tried not to repeat the errors form round 0 in the competition. 

         &lt;br&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Rounds 1-3&lt;/strong&gt; 
        &lt;br&gt;
        We made strategic decision not to introduce a new product. We decided to put our efforts and money in improving existing products, 2-3 in one round so that they are done before the end of the year. We also invested some money in automation and the maximum we could into marketing, but keeping in mind the cumulative margin of all products should be more than 30%. We based our estimations of produced units on best case estimation and our finance on the worst case estimation so that we don&#39;t need the emergency loan (because it has a very high percent). We were doing well growing slowly, but Andrew company was growing very fast and would probably take over in the round 4. 
 &lt;br&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Rounds 4-6&lt;/strong&gt; 
        &lt;br&gt;
        Unfortunately I could not stay in the class, but my colleagues informed me about the sort of our company. They took lots of risk in the round 4 in order to overcompete Andrew, they lowered down prices and they invested a lot in marketing. But it didn&#39;t work very well because all competitors lowered prices! Since then they went back to initial strategy. They tried make their products close to perfect and also invested in automation to increase the margin. With this strategy they finished first!!!
    &lt;/p&gt;
     &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/capsim_res.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Team work&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/team.jpg-large&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        I have a great chance to work in a team where decision making was not a big problem. Most of emotion raised the debate about introducing or not a new product. We manage to discuss and decided together. It was probably not the case for all teams. CAPSIM&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; simulation is a great exercise of team work and tested our capability of debate and decision making. 
       
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        The CBA course is great opportunity to get some glimpse of corporate life during a Ph. D. It helps to have general culture of enterprise, helps to develop logical thinking. The business simulations gives some brief hands on. But probably most importantly is an unique chance to meet great people that are in the same mindset and that can mutually help each other in career development. I cannot wait to the second part of the course in February 2017. 
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h6&gt;Practical info&lt;/h6&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        In order to apply to CBA check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cfdip.uspc.fr/fr/formations/catalogue-des-formations/metiers-entreprises-autres-organisations/innovation-entreprise/item/199-certificate-in-business-and-administration&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;webpage of the course&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/CBA/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/CBA/</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
