<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Urszula Czerwinska</title>
    <description>Science &amp;#x2192; Data Science</description>
    <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 09:55:37 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 09:55:37 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Student Council Symposium at Orlando</title>
        <description>&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Student Council Symposium at Orlando #SCSOrlando2016&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started off ISMB2016 by attending the Student Council Symposium. This meeting is dedicated to students, post docs, and young researchers in the fields of Computational Biology and Bioinformatics and it gave me a chance to present my work with an oral presentation and a poster.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The day started with an Ice Breaking event:&lt;strong&gt; Scientific speed dating. &lt;/strong&gt;We were given a few minutes to get introduced to other person present in the room. Despite myself (and many others) being massively jet-lagged, it was quite entertaining and it gave us the impression that you were continuing the day with friends, instead of strangers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/jq_Fotor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;First keynote speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: John Quackenbush, professor of Computational Biology and Biology and Bioinformatics, talked to us about some of his main research lines these days entitled &lt;em&gt;Networks from gentoype to phenotype.&lt;/em&gt; The main highlight of his talk was his network-based analysis coupled with transcriptomic and mutation data. He introduced an approach where he constructed networks specific to patients and then he compared their structure described in “&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1505.06440&quot; data-href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1505.06440&quot; class=&quot;markup--anchor markup--p-anchor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Estimating sample-specific regulatory networks&lt;/a&gt;”. He then criticized some of classical approaches calling them a ‘bio-poetry’. He also gave us quick overview of his approach to SNPs and eQTLs. He then went on to describe how important interdisciplinarity when working in computational biology is, using the example of implementing matrix formulation from quantum physics to describe network transitions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There were &lt;strong&gt;15 students presenting&lt;/strong&gt; for 15minutes each. This years most represented topics were protein structure reconstruction and sequence analysis. Some students shared their reflection on being in between two disciplines: biology &amp;amp; computer science. I personally found all talks very well prepared, most of speakers were clear and interesting. The participants came from different countries all around the world and some, like me, made it thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://symposium.iscbsc.org/tf-announcement&quot; data-href=&quot;http://symposium.iscbsc.org/tf-announcement&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ISCB travel fellowship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/jt_Fotor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;The second keynote&lt;/strong&gt; talk was given by Janet Thornton. She is Director Emeritus of EMBL-EBI and Senior Scientist, with scientific interest in protein structure. She not only shared with us an overview of her career path and research, but also personal reflections on different steps of her life: student, post-doc, PI. She left us with lots of very useful tips. She is a very warm and humble person and is a great example for many researchers. She expressed her belief that computational biology is an expanding field and that this will create job opportunities for young researchers. She was very passionate and happy about her unexpected career path she made from physics to computational biology.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/advice.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Elsevier, the sponsor of SCS, prepared also for us a special demo of their new product &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elsevier.com/solutions/pathway-studio-biological-research&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pathway Studio&lt;/a&gt; and offered us a free trial! They were very patient guiding us through their step-by-step tutorial and answering numerous questions.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Symposium ended with a &lt;strong&gt;poster session &lt;/strong&gt;which was accompanied with some snacks.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Participants then voted for the best poster and talk. The winners are to announced on Monday during ISCB Town Hall (!!!)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We were also invited to closing &lt;strong&gt;social event&lt;/strong&gt; when we could talk to our peers.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SCS was for me a great start to my trip. It was great to see other passionate students and discuss engaging research topics. Hope to cross paths with them again over the course of the main ISMB conference.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the SCS, I still had some time to explore the Swan &amp;amp; Dolphin hotel area. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hote.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;hr&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;/strong&gt;Any views expressed are those of the author, not necessarily those of PLOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;footer&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on July 11, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/bba71aad7353&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;View the original&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/scs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/scs</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
        <category>conferenceISMB2016</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Learning business at Sorbonne</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;i&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy, Finance and Marketing.&lt;/strong&gt; Why should I care about them if I am a Ph. D. student? Leave stereotypes behind and find out.&lt;/i&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;What is CBA?&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        Certificate in Business and Administration is a course organized by &lt;a href=&quot;http://cfdip.uspc.fr/fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CFDiP&lt;/a&gt; for students of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sorbonne-paris-cite.fr/en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Université Sorbonne Paris Cité&lt;/a&gt;. It has been inspired by best American Universities that propose CBA for their graduate students. It is happening in two steps of 7 and 5 days separated by 6 months. Entirely in English, CBA targets motivated Ph. D. students from different fields that are interested in pursuing their career outside of academia. It fills the gap in the current educational system that not prepare STEM students to land jobs in private sector. The program not only gives an overview of how company and business works. But, even more importantly gives an on-hand experience in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.capsim.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Capsim Business Simulator&lt;/a&gt; as it is done in top Business Schools. Here is a snapshot of the first week of the CBA challenge. Check also  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?src=typd&amp;q=%23CBAsorbonne&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;#CBASorbonne&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PxGirard&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@px.girard&lt;/a&gt;. 
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/strategy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
        Why companies pay consultants? What make a company grow and develop and other go bankrupt in the same environment? These were questions our teacher and the course coordinator &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:px.girard@gmail.com&quot;&gt;Pierre Girard&lt;/a&gt; addressed in his lecture about strategy. We learned how to analyze environment through PESTEL on a real-life study cases. We were also introduced also to ethics and the life cycle of companies. This gave us a general overview of what external factors weight most for company success and what matters we can face one working in or running a firm.
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Finance&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/finance.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        Second day was scarified to financial matters. Jiri Tresl explained us the difference between accounting and finance where the first one is the module providing information and the second taking decision and thus they both are inseparable to run a company. 
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Finance is an art of money management&lt;/blockquote&gt;
        We have been introduced to the whole new vocabulary: assets, investments, cash, liability, equity, shares, stocks, bonds and debts. We learned basic rules determining these alien world. Since  then we will all remember that 
                &lt;blockquote&gt;profit does NOT equal cash&lt;/blockquote&gt;
        This class really served us to understand how to manage finance of our virtual company in CAPSIM&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt;!

    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Marketing&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CCosine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Finally &#39;the key to business success&#39; - marketing. With dynamic Christine Coisne we went trough tactics and concepts. We studied evolution of company LEGO what is the difference between Transactional  and relational marketing, how to perform SWOT analysis and targets differentiation. Now for sure, we will not take &#39;marketing mix&#39; for a name of a drink and we will not think Maslow was a pharaoh of ancient Egypt. 
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;They made it!&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Meeting people that made career transition&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;Maureen Alivon&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;She has a bachelor in biology and master in pharmacology. She worked in a lab of Hôpital Européen Georges Pompidou about the effects of antiangiogenic drugs on large arteries elastic properties and she got the CBA certificate during her Ph.D. And after her Ph. D. she was asking herself a question what to do. She decided to look for a job outside of academia. However it was not easy. She has sent lots of CV. She event went though interview process to hear she cannot work in marketing because she has no experience. A situation we probably hear about. Finally, 3 months after her Ph. D. defense she got recommended for Medical Communication Manager in Servier. And she enjoys her job a lot. She shared with us some tips answered generously our questions. At first place, she highlighted that Ph. D. is a big thing and everything we will learn about time and work management will be useful in our future job. She advised not to wait for engage career transition. Faster the better, in order to build our professional network. She admitted she was not good with social media and not engaged in associative activities but it can definitely help to get a job. Even though she is not continuing on making experiments and she cannot publish, she highly appreciate her actual position and she is climbing up on the corporate ladder becoming project manager in upcoming month. 
    &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;Noemie Ballot&lt;/h4&gt; 
                &lt;p&gt;She is now a manager of European Project Green Nano Films and in parallel works for a start-up. She told us her way from Ph.D. in Material Chemistry to project management. She found her job thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.intelliagence.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ABG L&#39;intelli&#39;agence&lt;/a&gt;. She said the CBA experience gave her curiosity to learn more about management, leadership, teamwork, finance budget and helped her to practice English. As Maureen she highlighted importance of building a professional network early in the career. She said we need to talk about our job search to everyone around, use social media. She encouraged us to just talk about what we do with passion and project ourselves in different jobs with our motivation and skills, to be confident and open-minded. She listed for us some possible jobs after Ph.D.:
                
                        &lt;ul&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;R&amp;D&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;research in companies&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;science monitoring&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;patents&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;leadership consulting&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;research projects management&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;science communication&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;scientific editor&lt;/li&gt;

                        &lt;/ul&gt;

                    She shared also some platforms we can look for job:
                &lt;ul&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.intelliagence.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ABG L&#39;intelli&#39;agence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apec.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;APEC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Linekdin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fr.viadeo.com/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Viadeo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cadremploi.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cadremploi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/naturejobs/science/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Naturejobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                        

                        &lt;/ul&gt;
                &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;h4&gt;Nesrine Benyahia&lt;/h4&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;
                Our last guest Nesrine is still a Ph. D. student in health law while working for a start up  - consulting firm &lt;a href=&quot;http://bmcconsultingfrance.wix.com/bmcconsulting&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BMC Consulting&lt;/a&gt; she founded together  with two friends with law and business backgrounds. We asked her how she manages to carry on her Ph. D. and work at the same time. She confirmed it is not easy to have several tasks and that she works everywhere, in the metro, on weekends etc. but it is worth the hassle. 
            &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;CAPSIM&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; Business Simulation&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        The most exciting part of the course was a competition in CAPSIM&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; business simulator. For 4 days, six teams of 5-6 members managing each a B2B company producing sensors. There are five main sectors and each team starts with one product in one sector: High End, Low End, Traditional, Size and Performance. We had to manage R&amp;D, Marketing, Production and Finance. The competition was on for 6 rounds I was in Digby team with 4 great fellows: Clara, Rawan, Charlotte and Nirmal. I will share with you some of our strategy
        &lt;br&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Round 0&lt;/strong&gt; 
        &lt;br&gt;
        In the round 0 we had a chance to learn how to use the simulation and test some strategies. We decided to create a new product in High End as the age was the most important criterion for this sector. To estimate how much money we need to borrow and how many units we need produce we made positive and negatives estimations. We quickly realized that releasing new product is really costly and doesn&#39;t bring returns for at least 2 rounds. On the top it makes impossible to improve other products because R&amp;D works on the new products. We also took too much debt and we sold out on some products. We have seen also powerful impact of marketing where a similar product would sold much better if its awareness and accessibility were high. We tried not to repeat the errors form round 0 in the competition. 

         &lt;br&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Rounds 1-3&lt;/strong&gt; 
        &lt;br&gt;
        We made strategic decision not to introduce a new product. We decided to put our efforts and money in improving existing products, 2-3 in one round so that they are done before the end of the year. We also invested some money in automation and the maximum we could into marketing, but keeping in mind the cumulative margin of all products should be more than 30%. We based our estimations of produced units on best case estimation and our finance on the worst case estimation so that we don&#39;t need the emergency loan (because it has a very high percent). We were doing well growing slowly, but Andrew company was growing very fast and would probably take over in the round 4. 
 &lt;br&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Rounds 4-6&lt;/strong&gt; 
        &lt;br&gt;
        Unfortunately I could not stay in the class, but my colleagues informed me about the sort of our company. They took lots of risk in the round 4 in order to overcompete Andrew, they lowered down prices and they invested a lot in marketing. But it didn&#39;t work very well because all competitors lowered prices! Since then they went back to initial strategy. They tried make their products close to perfect and also invested in automation to increase the margin. With this strategy they finished first!!!
    &lt;/p&gt;
     &lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/capsim_res.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Team work&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/team.jpg-large&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        I have a great chance to work in a team where decision making was not a big problem. Most of emotion raised the debate about introducing or not a new product. We manage to discuss and decided together. It was probably not the case for all teams. CAPSIM&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; simulation is a great exercise of team work and tested our capability of debate and decision making. 
       
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        The CBA course is great opportunity to get some glimpse of corporate life during a Ph. D. It helps to have general culture of enterprise, helps to develop logical thinking. The business simulations gives some brief hands on. But probably most importantly is an unique chance to meet great people that are in the same mindset and that can mutually help each other in career development. I cannot wait to the second part of the course in February 2017. 
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h6&gt;Practical info&lt;/h6&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        In order to apply to CBA check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cfdip.uspc.fr/fr/formations/catalogue-des-formations/professionnelles-appliquees/mileu-de-l-entreprise-organisation-et-metiers-de-l-entreprise/item/199-certificate-in-business-and-administration&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;webpage of the course&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/CBA/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/CBA/</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Blogging at ISMB2016 Florida for Plos Computational Biology</title>
        <description>&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Blogging at #SCSOrlando2016 and #ISMB2016 for #PLOSCB&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In a week I will be attending SCS and ISMB 2016 in Orlando Walt Disney World Resort. Awesome, huh? I joined PLOSCB bloggers crew to blog for you about &lt;strong&gt;Student Council Symposium&lt;/strong&gt; #SCSOrlando2016, &lt;strong&gt;Carrer Development&lt;/strong&gt; #BoF and &lt;strong&gt;#bigdata&lt;/strong&gt; topics.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;hr&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t hesitate to meet me at my oral presentation of poster and poster sessions:
        &lt;blockquote&gt;DECONVOLUTION OF CELL AND ENVIRONMENT SPECIFIC SIGNALS AND THEIR INTERACTIONS FROM COMPLEX MIXTURES IN BIOLOGICAL SAMPLES&lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;SCS&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;h5&gt;Talk&lt;/h5&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time: &lt;/strong&gt;Friday, July 8, 4:15 pm — 4:30 pm &lt;strong&gt;Room: &lt;/strong&gt;Parrot (Swan Hall) &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posterismb.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/docs/Urszula_Czerwinska_ISMB2016.pdf&quot; &gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-download fa-1x&quot; &gt;&lt;/i&gt; Download&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;h5&gt;Poster session&lt;/h5&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 6:05 pm — 8:00 pm &lt;strong&gt;Room: &lt;/strong&gt;Parrot (Swan Hall)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;ISMB Poster #OP17&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;h5&gt;Talk&lt;/h5&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; Sunday, July 10, 11:40 am — 12:40 pm &lt;strong&gt;Room: &lt;/strong&gt;America’s Seminar&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h5&gt;Poster session&lt;/h5&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On display&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time: &lt;/strong&gt;Monday, July 11, 10:00 a.m. through Tuesday, July 12, 2:30 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With authors&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time: &lt;/strong&gt;Monday,&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;July 11,&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;5:40 pm — 7:30 pm &lt;strong&gt;Room: &lt;/strong&gt;Southern Hemisphere Ballroom&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i&gt;See you there, under the sun of Florida!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;hr&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;/strong&gt;Any views expressed are those of the author, not necessarily those of PLOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;footer&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on June 29, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/42108db287ac&quot;&gt;View the original&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/intro</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/intro</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
        <category>conferenceISMB2016</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>HelloWorld</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a HelloWorld post&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is R code test&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;print(&#39;Hello World&#39;)&lt;/code&gt;`&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/new%20cathegory/helloworld.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/new%20cathegory/helloworld.html</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
        <category>new cathegory</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Last topic in group</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This about sums it all up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/topics/my%20topic%20group/subcattest-topic3.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/topics/my%20topic%20group/subcattest-topic3.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>topics</category>
        
        <category>my topic group</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Deconvolution of mixed samples</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-icon-and-link&quot;&gt;Github icon and link&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short summary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section&quot;&gt;#&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;dont put unpublished results
update when it is published&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/DEconvolutionofTME.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/DEconvolutionofTME.html</guid>
        
        <category>Unsupervised learning</category>
        
        <category>ICA</category>
        
        <category>R</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>some reflection about data</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here we go.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/data/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/data/</guid>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
        <category>data</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Isotonic regression</title>
        <description>	&lt;h3&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Embed pdf&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Vestibulum ultrices risus velit, sit amet blandit massa auctor sit amet. Sed eu lectus sem. Phasellus in odio at ipsum porttitor mollis id vel diam. Praesent sit amet posuere risus, eu faucibus lectus. Vivamus ex ligula, tempus pulvinar ipsum in, auctor porta quam. Proin nec dui cursus, posuere dui eget interdum. Fusce lectus magna, sagittis at facilisis vitae, pellentesque at etiam. Quisque posuere leo quis sem commodo, vel scelerisque nisi scelerisque. Suspendisse id quam vel tortor tincidunt suscipit. Nullam auctor orci eu dolor consectetur, interdum ullamcorper ante tincidunt. Mauris felis nec felis elementum varius.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;
	&lt;h4&gt;Feugiat aliquam&lt;/h4&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Nam sapien ante, varius in pulvinar vitae, rhoncus id massa. Donec varius ex in mauris ornare, eget euismod urna egestas. Etiam lacinia tempor ipsum, sodales porttitor justo. Aliquam dolor quam, semper in tortor eu, volutpat efficitur quam. Fusce nec fermentum nisl. Aenean erat diam, tempus aliquet erat.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Etiam iaculis nulla ipsum, et pharetra libero rhoncus ut. Phasellus rutrum cursus velit, eget condimentum nunc blandit vel. In at pulvinar lectus. Morbi diam ante, vulputate et imperdiet eget, fermentum non dolor. Ut eleifend sagittis tincidunt. Sed viverra commodo mi, ac rhoncus justo. Duis neque ligula, elementum ut enim vel, posuere finibus justo. Vivamus facilisis maximus nibh quis pulvinar. Quisque hendrerit in ipsum id tellus facilisis fermentum. Proin mauris dui, at vestibulum sit amet, auctor bibendum neque.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/Dengue.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/Dengue.html</guid>
        
        <category>Algorithm benchmarking</category>
        
        <category>Matematica</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to data vizualization [FR]</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-icon-and-link&quot;&gt;Github icon and link&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short summary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section&quot;&gt;#&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;generate with knitr::&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/TP_R.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/TP_R.html</guid>
        
        <category>Teaching</category>
        
        <category>R</category>
        
        <category>Data viz</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Teen spirit</title>
        <description>	&lt;h3&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Embed pdf&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;copy some stuff from igem wiki&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;
	&lt;h4&gt;Feugiat aliquam&lt;/h4&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Nam sapien ante, varius in pulvinar vitae, rhoncus id massa. Donec varius ex in mauris ornare, eget euismod urna egestas. Etiam lacinia tempor ipsum, sodales porttitor justo. Aliquam dolor quam, semper in tortor eu, volutpat efficitur quam. Fusce nec fermentum nisl. Aenean erat diam, tempus aliquet erat.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Etiam iaculis nulla ipsum, et pharetra libero rhoncus ut. Phasellus rutrum cursus velit, eget condimentum nunc blandit vel. In at pulvinar lectus. Morbi diam ante, vulputate et imperdiet eget, fermentum non dolor. Ut eleifend sagittis tincidunt. Sed viverra commodo mi, ac rhoncus justo. Duis neque ligula, elementum ut enim vel, posuere finibus justo. Vivamus facilisis maximus nibh quis pulvinar. Quisque hendrerit in ipsum id tellus facilisis fermentum. Proin mauris dui, at vestibulum sit amet, auctor bibendum neque.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/iGEM.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/iGEM.html</guid>
        
        <category>Synthetic biology</category>
        
        <category>Product design</category>
        
        <category>Graphical design</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
