<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Urszula Czerwinska</title>
    <description>Science &amp;#x2192; Data Science</description>
    <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 21:52:40 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 21:52:40 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Named Entity Recognition - keywords detection from Medium articles</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by a solution developed for a customer in the Pharmaceutical industry,we presented at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://paris.egg.dataiku.com/&quot;&gt;EGG PARIS 2019&lt;/a&gt;conference an application based on NLP (Natural Language Processing) and developed on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dataiku.com/&quot;&gt;Dataiku&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dataiku.com/dss/&quot;&gt;DSS&lt;/a&gt; environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More precisely, we trained a deep learning model to recognize the keywords of a blog article, precisely from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/&quot;&gt;Medium blogging platform&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This solution applied to blog articles can be used to &lt;strong&gt;automatically generate tags and/or keywords&lt;/strong&gt; so that the content offered by the platforms is personalized and meets readers’ expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a broad sense, entity detection allows automated and intelligent text analysis, especially useful for long and complex documents such as scientific or legal pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate its use, we have integrated a voice command, based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/services/cognitive-services/&quot;&gt;Azure’s cognitive services API&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;speech to text&lt;/em&gt; module allows to return query text as input to the algorithm. The output is represented as a recommendation of articles, classified by relevance according to the field of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article explains our approach to creating the underlying NLP model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zg0pTe-GyF0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[to view the comments, please enable subtitles] A video that illustrates our web application  created for the EGG Dataiku 2019 conference&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-extract-keywords-from-medium-blog-articles&quot;&gt;Why extract keywords from Medium blog articles?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medium has two categorization systems: &lt;strong&gt;tags&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;topics&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topics are imposed by the platform. The author cannot select his topic. They correspond to fairly generic categories such as data science or machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tags, a maximum of 5 per article, are essentially keywords that the author decides to list under his post in order to make it visible. Thus an article may have tags that may have nothing to do with the content of the article/history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you label it with common terms, such as “TECHNOLOGY” or “MINDFULNESS” or “LOVE” or “LIFE LESSONS”, your item will be easier to find. But it makes life more difficult for a reader who is looking for a specific subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will therefore try to self-tag articles to increase their relevance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to these “new tags”, or “keywords”, we could quickly search for the articles that mention them and thus increase the effectiveness of our search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could go even further and build a recommendation system, by advising articles close to the one we are reading, or by advising ourselves of new articles related to our reading habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ner-named-entity-recognition-approach&quot;&gt;The NER (Named Entity Recognition) approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the NER (Named Entity Recognition) approach, it is possible to extract entities from different categories. There are several basic  pre-trained models, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/explosion/spacy-models/releases/tag/en_core_web_md-2.2.0&quot;&gt;en_core_web_md&lt;/a&gt;, which is able to recognize people, places, dates…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take the example of the sentence &lt;em&gt;I think Barack Obama puts founder of Facebook at occasion of a release of a new NLP algorithm&lt;/em&gt;. The en_core_web_md model detects Facebook and Barack Obama as entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/UrszulaCzerwinska/11a8fab0cc4c936b67e374e2b55e0fa0.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Dependency graph: result of line 9 (# 1)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Entity detection: result of line 10 (# 2)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our use case : extracting topics from Medium articles, we would like the model to recognize an additional entity in the “TOPIC” category: “NLP algorithm”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some annotated data we can “teach” the algorithm to detect a new type of entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is simple: an article tagged Data Science, AI, Machine Learning, Python can concern very different technologies. Our algorithm would thus be able to detect a specific technology cited in the article, for example GAN, reinforcement learning, or the names of python libraries used. It also retains the ability of a basic model to recognize places, names of organizations and names of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During training, the model learns to recognize the keywords, without knowing them a priori. The model will be able to recognize for example the topic: random forest without even being present in the learning data. Based on articles that discuss other algorithms (e.g. linear regression), the NER model will be able to recognize the phrase turn of phrase that indicates that we are talking about an algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-model&quot;&gt;The model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spacy-framework&quot;&gt;SpaCy Framework&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://spacy.io/&quot;&gt;SpaCy&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source library for advanced natural language processing in Python. It is designed specifically for use in production and helps to build applications that handle large volumes of text. It can be used to build information extraction systems, natural language comprehension systems or text preprocessing systems for in-depth learning. Among the functions offered by SpaCy are: Tokenization, Parts-of-Speech (PoS) Tagging, Text Classification and Named Entity Recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SpaCy provides an exceptionally efficient statistical system for NER in python. In addition to entities included by default, SpaCy also gives us the freedom to add arbitrary classes to the NER model, training the model to update it with new examples formed.
SpaCy’s NER model is based on &lt;strong&gt;CNN&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;Convolutional Neural Networks&lt;/strong&gt;).
For the curious, the details of how SpaCy’s NER model works are explained in the video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sqDHBH9IjRU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-data&quot;&gt;Training data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start training the model to recognize tech keywords, we recovered some Medium articles through &lt;strong&gt;web scraping&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/UrszulaCzerwinska/db0aa37b1cb10ec94205d847f63ddc4f.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;An extract from the table containing the contents of the medium articles&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text of each article has been divided into sentences to facilitate annotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are annotation tools for NER such as Prodigy or other, mentioned here. We used a simple spreadsheet and in the dedicated columns we marked the entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give an idea of the volume required, with about twenty articles (~600 sentences) our model started to show an interesting performance (&amp;gt;0.78 accuracy on test set).
The train and test data were separated to evaluate the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TRAIN_DATA_ALL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;train_table&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mark_targets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;ORG&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;PERSON&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;LOC&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;TOPIC&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;GPE&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;DATE&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;EVENT&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;WORK_OF_ART&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;sents&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;ORG&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;PERSON&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;LOC&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;TOPIC&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;GPE&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;DATE&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;EVENT&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&#39;WORK_OF_ART&#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;axis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img6.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, we fine-tuned our algorithm by playing on several parameters: number of iterations, drop rate, learning rate and batch size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;model-assesment&quot;&gt;Model assesment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the loss metric of the model, we have implemented the indicators: precision, recall and F1 score, to more accurately measure the performance of our model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/UrszulaCzerwinska/c23ce9e0edffe6f9790a2bbf8f018a4b.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once trained on all the annotated data, the performance of the best model on our test set was quite impressive. Especially if we take into account the modest size of the train data: ~3000 sentences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;precision :  0.9588053949903661
recall :  0.9211764705882353
f1_score :  0.9396221959858323

It is is designed to interoperate with the Python numerical and scientific libraries NumPy and SciPy.

TOPIC Python
TOPIC NumPy
TOPIC SciPy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Flow&lt;/strong&gt; on DSS, the process can be summarized by the graph:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img7.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Flow on Dataiku&#39;s DSS platform: the annotated dataset is divided into train and test, the model learned on the train data is evaluated on the train and test batches.&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To return to the example on Barack Obama, our algorithm detects the &lt;em&gt;NLP algorithm&lt;/em&gt; entity as TOPIC in addition to the ORG (organization) and PERSON entities.
We have succeeded! 🚀&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img8.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finalized model can be compiled as an independent python library (instructions here) and installed with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt;. This is very practical for deploying the model in another environment and for production setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exploitation-of-the-model&quot;&gt;Exploitation of the model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;analysis-of-an-article-medium&quot;&gt;Analysis of an article Medium&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our mini webapp, presented at the EGG, it is possible to display the most frequent entities of a Medium article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, for the article: &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/cat-dog-or-elon-musk-145658489730&quot;&gt;https://towardsdatascience.com/cat-dog-or-elon-musk-145658489730&lt;/a&gt;, the most frequent entities were: model, MobileNet, Transfer learning, network, Python. We also detected people: Elon Musk, Marshal McLuhan and organizations: Google, Google Brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img10.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/@bramblexu&quot;&gt;Xu LIANG’s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/textrank-for-keyword-extraction-by-python-c0bae21bcec0&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, we also used his way of representing the relationship between words in the form of a graph of linguistic dependencies. Unlike in his method, we did not use TextRank or TFIDF to detect keywords but we only applied our pre-trained NER model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/@bramblexu&quot;&gt;Xu LIANG&lt;/a&gt;, we used the capacity of Parts-of-Speech (PoS) Tagging, inherited by our model from the original model (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/explosion/spacy-models/releases/tag/en_core_web_md-2.2.0&quot;&gt;en_core_web_md&lt;/a&gt;), to link the entities together with the edges, which forms the graph below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NER_img11.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;The graph of dependencies between the entities detected in the article “Cat, Dog, or Elon Musk?”&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we get a graph where the keywords are placed around their category: Tech topic, Person and Organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives a quick overview of the content of a Medium article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how to get the graph from a Medium article url link:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/UrszulaCzerwinska/d1d77f0bf8bd089103994eb3883db28f.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-go-further&quot;&gt;To go further&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Saegus Showroom including the functional webapp is coming soon. Feel free to follow our page &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/data-by-saegus&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/data-by-saegus&lt;/a&gt; to be kept informed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The project we have outlined here can easily be transposed into the various fields of industry: technical, legal and medical documents. It could be very interesting to analyse the civil, criminal and law… with this approach for a better efficiency in the research that all legal professionals do.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is a result of a teamwork realized at &lt;a href=&quot;http://saegus.com/fr/&quot;&gt;Saegus&lt;/a&gt;. Published originally in French at &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/data-by-saegus/ner-medium-articles-saegus-7ffec0f3188c&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/egg_ner</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/egg_ner</guid>
        
        <category>NLP</category>
        
        <category>Python</category>
        
        <category>Saegus</category>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Women in Healthcare Analytics and Data Science (WiHADS)</title>
        <description>&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
	&lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;


&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;   
&lt;section&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project started in 2017 for initiative of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/sameh-m-8575a3179/&quot;&gt;Sameh Megrhi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;The purpose of this group is to highlight the advances of Artificial Intelligence in the field of Health. We would like to give weight to profiles of women who have made significant contributions in this field in order to promote the place of women in this sector, which is still too often represented by men.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WiHADS meetup will engage data scientists, industry experts, researchers, medical.
        We set out to portray, encourage the community to discuss and share knowledge and experiences to help solve the most complex issues around data, analytics, privacy, standards, quality of care and discuss perspectives of the evolving use of Big Data in and healthcare and, to examine opportunities and challenges.
    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2017 four meetup evenings took place in Paris and we are not stopping there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Join us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/fr-FR/Healthcare-Analytics-Data-Science/&quot;&gt;our meetup webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The idea&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field of Data and Analytics is expanding in all sectors. It will have impact on the future of Economy, Education and Healthcare. Holding Ph.D. in Systems Biology and helping to solve Machine Learning problems in academia and pharma, I could observe how it is in the healthcare sector and the impact it can have on people lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My motivation for joining WiHADS in 2018 was to promote women role models, to learn from their experience and share our point of views. Also to build a strong professional network and help early-career women forge their path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/sameh-m-8575a3179/&quot;&gt;Sameh Megrhi&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/imen-helali-phd-a6a4222b/&quot;&gt; Imen Helali&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/avani-tanna-b20b8a77/&quot;&gt;Avani Tanna&lt;/a&gt; we developed our meetup formulae of 2-3 speakers, buffet and then round table debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hosted women speakers from IQvia, Doctolib, PhP, Cardiologs, Dr.Data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our organisation it fully pro-bono, entrance is free, place and food are provided thanks to our great sponsors. Our sponsors were: Doctolib, IQvia, Saegus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please contact us if you want to host a meetup or sponsor a buffet!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wihads3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=70% /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/wihads</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/wihads</guid>
        
        <category>data science</category>
        
        <category>events</category>
        
        <category>healthcare</category>
        
        <category>networking</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Language gap between academia and business</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
	&lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data
	science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;

&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body&gt;

	&lt;style&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;    	
		body { background-color:blue; }
		.highlightme { background-color:#ccffe5; }
 		&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/style&gt;


&lt;section&gt;
	&lt;h3&gt;Have you ever felt like you don&#39;t know how to put accurate words on your
		ideas when speaking with a business person?&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If like me you have been within the academic universe for some time
			and have tried to get a job in the private sector, you have probably
			realized it is not always easy to understand each other.

			On one side of the barrier, researchers and engineers. On the other,
			business professionals. Both species originating from the common
			Homo Sapiens Sapiens but which have developed divergent vocabulary
			and related behavior because of the environmental pressure.

			&lt;strong&gt;Jokes apart, the language of science and business are quite
				different and worth exploring.&lt;/strong&gt;
		&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;To begin with, let&#39;s compare the environment. In academia, the goal is to
		excel in some aspect and to be more innovative and original than others.
		This is why words commonly used (and overused) related to this aspect are:
		&lt;b&gt;novel&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;insight&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;paradigm&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;extremely&lt;/b&gt;,
		&lt;b&gt;elucidate&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;robust&lt;/b&gt;. The research often aims to
		understand and describe things, this is why it is common to talk about
		&lt;b&gt;landscapes&lt;/b&gt; and
		&lt;b&gt;frameworks&lt;/b&gt;. What counts is the global impact of the work, how
		broad it is. There is usually a hypothesis somewhere on the line,
		uncertainty that needs to be acknowledged to avoid the critics with
		&lt;b&gt;putative&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;respectively&lt;/b&gt;,
		&lt;b&gt;potentially&lt;/b&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/boss.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;It is also common to use &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; even for a one-person task or
		overusing the passive voice. This use of &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; often sounds odd to
		business people and results in an uncertainty of which part of the project
		you actually did yourself. &lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;h3&gt;Critical attitude&lt;/h3&gt;


	&lt;p&gt;
		Researches are trained to keep their critical spirit awake and challenge
		each other. One of the first things I was told at a &#39;how to get a job&#39;
		workshop for PhDs was to &lt;b&gt;be less critical&lt;/b&gt;. When I listen to my
		colleagues who are now working in business, I often hear phrases like
		&lt;b&gt;opportunities for improvement&lt;/b&gt; used instead of phrases like
		&lt;i&gt;pitfalls&lt;/i&gt;. When something is not working, it would be said that it
		is &lt;b&gt;in development&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;with growth potential&lt;/b&gt;. Spending longer
		than usual to understand a complex case is an investment in the company
		knowledge capital. Even firing employees can be called restructuring.
		Like it or not, attitude is different and working in a corporate
		universe means you should try to fit in and formulate your critiques
		with prudence.
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;h3&gt;Working culture&lt;/h3&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;Corporate people often prefer fast (and sometimes ugly) solutions, that
		minimize time and maximize profit. This why words such as &lt;b&gt;ballpark&lt;/b&gt;
		are often used. &lt;b&gt;Itemize&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;prioritize&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;agile&lt;/b&gt;,
		&lt;b&gt;takeaways&lt;/b&gt; show that time and task management plays an important role
		in the work culture. Another type of expressions are &lt;b&gt;incentivize&lt;/b&gt;,
		&lt;b&gt;proactive&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;repurpose&lt;/b&gt;, it reflects how dynamic the corporate
		world is. You are required to act and react quickly, find solutions rather
		than questions. It is common to talk about &lt;b&gt;empowerment&lt;/b&gt; and
		&lt;b&gt;leverage&lt;/b&gt; when discussing strategy, words that are rare in
		academia. Business is about money, therefore some expressions higlight
		value, profit, and material gains; such as &lt;b&gt;push the envelope&lt;/b&gt; and
		&lt;b&gt;added value&lt;/b&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;blockquote&gt;The difference in wording reflects different attitudes and
		methods used in business and research worlds. This does not mean that skills
		gained in one universe cannot be useful in the another. However, the
		competence one gains in research needs to be worded in a way it can be
		understood and considered useful in the corporate world.
		&lt;span class=&quot;highlightme&quot;&gt;
			&lt;b&gt;The skill of making yourself understood can really help foster a
				smooth transition into the business world.&lt;/b&gt; Communication, in
			general, is a very important skill for any team and a key factor for
			company success. &lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;
		A researcher, even when working in a team, is responsible for his
		project from A to Z. He or she communicates with other researches that
		already have a lot of knowledge about your topic. Conversely, in the
		corporate world, your work is just a part of a bigger process and so you
		need to properly communicate and document your work. This is why a lot
		of place in the corporate vernacular is given to the organization of
		work and management.
	&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;h3&gt;
		CV writing
	&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		Your journey to the corporate world starts with a CV. A researcher&#39;s CV
		is usually a very complete and long list of projects, contributions,
		presentations and publications in a chronological order. The CV you will
		send to hiring managers in the private sector should be quite different.
		Even though writing CVs is a whole different subject, I can advise you
		to follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.fr/us/google-exec-gives-key-to-perfect-resume-2014-9&quot;&gt;Google
			recommendations&lt;/a&gt; for tech jobs at least. The format and wording of
		your CV should be inspired by the corporate world and speak in a
		business tone. For example, instead of writing &#39;Studied system X in
		conditions A, B and published a paper entitled Novel landscape of system
		X indicates [very long technical word] in conditions A, B&#39;, you can
		write: &#39;Achieved Z/Improved by Z/Discovered Z when studying the system
		X&#39;. You should also add your logistical duties of the project for
		example &#39;Managed a team of N people/ (international) project&#39; or
		&#39;Monthly reported progress to an international commission in a form of
		dashboards and [format] presentations&#39;.


	&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;In the research world, the second wording may sound unnatural. Also, no
		one cares if and how you were reporting or managing your project if you
		published a great paper. In the private sector, the fixation over the
		publications is not well understood so it is hard for them to see what
		skills it takes to publish a journal paper. This is why such an achievement
		needs to be decomposed in smaller tasks that can be understood and valued. &lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/work.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;h3&gt;
		Tell me about your research
	&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		If you have never prepared an answer to this question, practice on your
		non-academic friends and/or family members, usually you lose your
		listener in the first two sentences. Start your response with why not with
		how, focus on the big picture, avoid technical words, scientific names
		and try to make parallels with every day or business life. You should
		always adapt your vocabulary to your interlocutor. Do not be afraid to
		speak too broadly, you can always go into specifics if they ask for more
		details on certain aspects that you mention in your pitch. To get
		inspired with short presentation format, you can have a look at
		guidelines for &lt;a href=&quot;http://thepostdocway.com/content/elevator-pitches-scientists-what-when-where-and-how&quot;&gt;elevator
			pitch &lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/threeminutethesis&quot;&gt;3MT&lt;/a&gt; videos.
	&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;h3&gt;
		Presentations
	&lt;/h3&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;Another form of communication often used in the business world are
		presentations, usually with support slides. In the private sector, presentations
		are used a lot. And if you think that the content matters more than the form,
		you are right. But, the &lt;b&gt;form is very important&lt;/b&gt;, much much more than in
		scientific word. The purpose of presentations is to persuade and inform your
		audience. This is why putting the big picture first, just like for the elevator
		pitch is crucial. Don’t neglect the visuals. Beautiful illustrations and tidy
		design can help develop your message.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;
		Final word
	&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		Even though there is a gap between science and business, it does not
		mean one cannot belong to both. It may take some effort, just like
		learning to speak another language but learning to adapt to the business
		world can give you a lot of satisfaction and open the doors. So go out
		to the world, participate in the events organized by the industry and
		converse with them. Do not get taken by surprise at your dream
		job/internship interview, it would be dull to miss it because of the
		content ‘lost in translation’. 


	&lt;/p&gt;
	
	&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/raising.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/html&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/businesslang</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/businesslang</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD Thesis</title>
        <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE HTML&gt;
&lt;html lang=&quot;en-US&quot;&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
        &lt;meta charset=&quot;UTF-8&quot;&gt;
        &lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;refresh&quot; content=&quot;1; url=&quot;&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
            window.location.href = &quot;https://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/UCzPhDThesis/&quot;
        &lt;/script&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Page Redirection&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
        &lt;!-- Note: don&#39;t tell people to `click` the link, just tell them that it is a link. --&gt;
        If you are not redirected automatically, follow this &lt;a href=&#39;https://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/UCzPhDThesis/&#39;&gt;link to example&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/PhDThesis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/PhDThesis.html</guid>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>R</category>
        
        <category>Data Science</category>
        
        <category>biomedical applications</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DeconICA</title>
        <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE HTML&gt;
&lt;html lang=&quot;en-US&quot;&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
        &lt;meta charset=&quot;UTF-8&quot;&gt;
        &lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;refresh&quot; content=&quot;1; url=&quot;&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
            window.location.href = &quot;https://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/DeconICA/&quot;
        &lt;/script&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Page Redirection&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
        &lt;!-- Note: don&#39;t tell people to `click` the link, just tell them that it is a link. --&gt;
        If you are not redirected automatically, follow this &lt;a href=&#39;https://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/DeconICA/&#39;&gt;link to example&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/deconica</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/deconica</guid>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>R</category>
        
        <category>Data Science</category>
        
        <category>Deconvolution</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Big Dive</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;

&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
    &lt;style&gt;
        .scalable {
            overflow: hidden;
        }

        .scalable iframe {
            height: 100%;
            left: 0;
            position: absolute;
            top: 0;
            width: 100%;
        }

        .scalable .scalable-content {
            height: 0;
            position: relative;
        }

        .scalable-16-9 .scalable-content {
            /* Percentage from 9 divided by 16 for ratio of 16:9. */
            padding-bottom: 56.25%;
        }

        iframe {display:block;margin:auto;width: 100%}


    &lt;/style&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;section&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;i&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big data - big unknown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;When we play with data that are not so big... &lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        Experience with big data is among top skills of a data scientist profile.  However,  it is not trivial to learn big data tools without necessary infrastructure and proper tutoring. While pursuing my PhD in Data science dealing with medium size data frames (&lt; 1G),  usually all can be processed on one machine. In order to get some taste of methods and challenges of Big Data,  I completed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bigdive.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Big Dive&lt;/a&gt; course organized by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.top-ix.org/en/home-eng/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TOP-IX&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;... but we want to get a taste of &lt;strong&gt;BIG data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/companies.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image rights TOP-IX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
       During the intense 5-week course I put in practice my Python - pandas skills and learned new libraries for &lt;b&gt;distributed computing&lt;/b&gt;,  as well as &lt;i&gt;Py&lt;b&gt;Spark&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; basics.  We also spent a significant amount of time setting up the infrastructure on &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/fr/?nc2=h_lg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;amazon aws&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mongodb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;MongoDB&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Invited keynote speakers showed us important aspects and challenges of the data science for &lt;b&gt;business and science&lt;/b&gt;. A bonus was an introduction to beautiful &lt;b&gt;visualization D3.js&lt;/b&gt;. Finally, for me the most interesting and important part of the course was a &lt;b&gt;project&lt;/b&gt; realized for one of 3 companies: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifc.org/wps/wcm/connect/corp_ext_content/ifc_external_corporate_site/home&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IFC&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://eduscopio.it/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Eduscopio&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tesisquare.com/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TesiSquare&lt;/a&gt; where in just a few days we put our best efforts to make sense of hundreds of gigabytes of data!
      

        


    &lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;h3&gt;About the course&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        
        The course took place in a group of 20 students, with STEM/linguistic/design background, mostly from Italy but there were also a few foreign folks like me. Our diversity helped a lot during the group project when each of us could bring different perspective and skillset.
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
         &lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bigdive6-WELCOME_def.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image rights TOP-IX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        In order to apply, a candidate needs to send a video explaining why he or she is a good fit for the big dive as well as state level of her/his prerequisites. 
        &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
        If you want to read more about the content of the course you can check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bigdive.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Big Dive website&lt;/a&gt; as well as read their great &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/christianracca/detail/recent-activity/posts/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;posts on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/christianracca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Christian Racca&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/bigdive.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bigdive_eu&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;twitter @bigdive_eu&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
        For most of the participants and for me it was the first time with Big data.  I found the possibility to face the problems and tools I don&#39;t encounter in my everyday work. The content of the course was quite densely packed and I will need some time after the course to practice new skills and read all material. Thanks to great teachers like among others &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/alexcomu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alex Comunian&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/abusedmedia/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fabio Franchino&lt;/a&gt; classes were very interactive and easy to follow. 
&lt;div class=&quot;scalable scalable-16-9&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;scalable-content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/y1Zj_pOx_iE&quot;  allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;em&gt;Big Dive Yearbook 2017&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Personal highlights&lt;/h3&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The course was great &lt;b&gt;networking&lt;/b&gt; opportunity, partner companies posted their job openings, as well as a CV repository, was created by course organizers to facilitate their job search, also other participants of the course are new connections in my professional network that can be priceless in the future&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;D3.js&lt;/b&gt; is a very powerful tool for data visualization but its learning curve is quite steep. Learning jquery and communication with a remote data server, basics of web design are necessary to create a serious final product. So if you don&#39;t want to spend a significant amount of time learning all the toolkit better go for pre-set solutions like RShiny if you know R for instance.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Dask&lt;/b&gt; library seems to be  an interesting alternative to Spark for smaller projects, the big plus is that it is using pandas vocabulary. It can be also misleading as we encountered quite a lot of problems building a set up for our data, lots of ram memory seems to be necessary and understanding how dask is dealing with our objects differently than pandas is crucial for a successful application. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Spark&lt;/b&gt; contains important differences in algorithms from R or scikit-learn implementations. Therefore testing locally and comparing to the distributed version is not a good idea and difference in performance can be significant. It is important to keep it in mind from the beginning of the project. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Github&lt;/b&gt; has some really cool project management features like issues system and wiki. Usually, it is not extensively used in academia or only as a code repository while for us the management part was really useful and handy to organize work. If you are a student you can get a &lt;a href=&quot;https://education.github.com/pack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Student Developer Pack for free&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We got a refreshment about &lt;b&gt;ML&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;network science&lt;/b&gt;, together with some cool mini project implementations (like twitter API analysis) that can be a great starting point for a demo project one can use for its portfolio. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A &lt;b&gt;field expert&lt;/b&gt; is an important part of the team. His needs should guide the analysis, it helps to make data scientist work really useful in the domain of its application &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/dataring.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/copyrights.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 

    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Data ring&lt;/b&gt; - a tool proposed by top-ix and IFC helps to plan the project and communicate within data science team and with the business partner. You can find more information about in the comprehensive handbook &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifc.org/wps/wcm/connect/22ca3a7a-4ee6-444a-858e-374d88354d97/IFC+Data+HandBook+FINAL.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DATA ANALYTICS AND DIGITAL FINANCIAL SERVICES&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In my project, I worked with e-money transaction data and I found the problematic pretty interesting, it encouraged me to read finance and economy articles. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/final.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image rights TOP-IX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
   
        &lt;h3&gt;Final comments&lt;/h3&gt;
        
         
    &lt;p&gt; 
    Even if you cannot become an expert in big data in 5 weeks this course was a great intro to new concepts.  It was also a lot of fun,  intense immersion in Italian culture with lots of sun and pizza. Don&#39;t hesitate to contact me if you want to hear more about the course.
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bigdive.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image rights TOP-IX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Useful links&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bigdive.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Big Dive website&lt;/b&gt;: http://www.bigdive.eu/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/christianracca/detail/recent-activity/posts/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;posts on LinkedIn&lt;/b&gt;: https://www.linkedin.com/in/christianracca/detail/recent-activity/posts/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/bigdive.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Facebook page&lt;/b&gt;: https://www.facebook.com/bigdive.eu/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bigdive_eu&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;twitter&lt;/b&gt;: @bigdive_eu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kdnuggets.com/2016/04/data-science-comprehensive-guide-transition.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;post that inspired me to participate in Big DIVE : From Science to Data Science, a Comprehensive Guide for Transition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;I would like to thank Amodsen Chiota and Pierre Girard for their support for my application. As well as my PhD supervisor Andrei Zinovyev for allowing to participate in the course during my PhD time. 
Funding was provided by “Ecole Doctorale Frontières du Vivant (FdV) – Programme Bettencourt.”
&lt;/p&gt;
            
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/bigdive/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/bigdive/</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hi, I am Computational Biologist</title>
        <description>&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
	&lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;


&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body&gt;

	&lt;style&gt;
		.scalable {
			overflow: hidden;
		}

		.scalable iframe {
			height: 100%;
			left: 0;
			position: absolute;
			top: 0;
			width: 100%;
		}

		.scalable .scalable-content {
			height: 0;
			position: relative;
		}

		.scalable-16-9 .scalable-content {
			/* Percentage from 9 divided by 16 for ratio of 16:9. */
			padding-bottom: 56.25%;
		}

		iframe {display:block;margin:auto;width: 100%}


	&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;/body&gt;   
&lt;section&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		&lt;blockquote&gt;Hi, I am Computational Biologist, would you hire me when I graduate (from PhD)?&lt;/blockquote&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;h3&gt;Thinking about a job&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		I am in my second year of PhD in Computational Biology / Systems Biology at Cancer Institute in France. It is almost halfway to graduation here, where PhD needs to be completed in 3-4 years, so I reckon it is a right time to find out personally how are my chances of getting a job in the &lt;b&gt;data science&lt;/b&gt; market. So I asked the question &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hi, I am Computational Biologist, would you hire me when I graduate (from PhD)?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; in many declinations to different companies. I would like to share with you my experience from four &lt;strong&gt;job fairs&lt;/strong&gt;, I attended in November in Paris. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Let me start from the end...&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;h3&gt;To make the long story short - key messages (for busy ones)&lt;/h3&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;many companies will not know what &lt;b&gt;computational biology&lt;/b&gt; is -  so adapt your title to the company - i.e. &lt;i&gt;data analyst of biological/ genetic data / for medical sciences&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;data scientist in (biological) research&lt;/i&gt;  etc. in order to highlight your actual role &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;most of companies may not be familiar with qualities you can bring as a PhD graduate - work on communication of your transferable skills, convince them your are more than just a student that took longer to get a degree &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;you might hear that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/qualities-google-looks-for-in-job-candidates-2014-4?IR=T&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Google does want people with high &quot;cognitive ability&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; so you may think it is enough to be smart to get a position - even though your learning capability and intelligence are strong assets, &lt;b&gt;most of companies are not Google&lt;/b&gt;, they are &lt;b&gt;looking for solid skills&lt;/b&gt; that they will test in a technical interview i.e. your coding skills, your strategical thinking, situation analysis, problem solving. &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;in most cases, PhD graduates are treated the same way as fresh graduates from a master/engineer degree - it is rare there are predefined posts for PhD holders, you posses, for sure, different qualities and experience, which can be a plus, but don&#39;t wait for an applause, &lt;b&gt;be flexible&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; Programming in &lt;b&gt;R&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;Python&lt;/b&gt; or &lt;b&gt;SAS&lt;/b&gt; is the base (not a surprise) for data science&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;skills in &lt;b&gt;data visualization, database management, big data tools&lt;/b&gt; can be something that distinct you from other candidates&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;scientific writing&lt;/b&gt; and the whole communication toolbox, can also be a big plus, some companies release internal white papers and writing skills are highly valued &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;there is a huge need for skills of computational biologists in diverse projects in industry - lots of start-up with crazy ideas, challenging projects, there world is big out there &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;show you interest in a specific sector of industry, even an on-line course can be a plus, attend some meet-ups or events to feel the general ambiance and hot topics of the sector &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;ask questions and listen to HR advice - some of HR, especially in start-ups are actually working on projects that may interest you; some of them are new hires and they are happy to give you advice on how to get into the company&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;hiring procedures of companies&lt;/b&gt;, even with very similar profiles can be very different - take time to ask about hiring procedures, go to &lt;a href=https://www.glassdoor.fr/index.htm target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;glassdoor&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, reach company employees on LinkedIn &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;t is fine to submit your CV to employers before your finish your PhD — you never know — however, make sure you start &lt;b&gt;applying for jobs 6 months before the end of you PhD&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;add your non-academic experience to your CV, courses related to business. Do not put too many academic details, i.e. faculty full names, professors names — unless it is someone very well known— just speak the language they do.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;smile&lt;/b&gt;, have positive attitude - talk about your motivation for transition in a positive way&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;be cautious about your responsibilities, some companies, especially start-up would hire you to do everything related with data management, while what they need is a team of data analyst, not one PhD graduate &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;               

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The long story (for mindful ones)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	French educational system is complicated. To simplify, the university master and PhD is seen as a path exclusiv for academic career. This view is slowly changing and we hear more and more about companies hiring PhDs. Universities are also trying to promote alternative carriers organizing &#39;professional breakfasts&#39;, workshops, interview simulations or CV tuning (I have participated in some organized by &lt;a href=http://cfdip.uspc.fr/fr/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CFDiP&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=http://www.adoc-tm.com/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Adoc Talent Managment&lt;/a&gt;). There is even a &lt;a href=http://hub11.ecolearning.eu/course/doctorat-et-poursuite-de-carriere/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MOOC&lt;/a&gt; that should help PhDs orientate their careers. Also, recently title &lt;i&gt;Docteur-PhD&lt;/i&gt; has been officially recognized and there will be created a nation network for PhD holders with a yearbook and a standardized e-mail address system. 

	&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en-gb&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;fr&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Création d&amp;#39;un réseau des docteurs avec un annuaire annuel et une adresse mail : prenom.nom@phdfrance.fr &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sup_recherche&quot;&gt;@sup_recherche&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Thierry Mandon (@mandonthierry) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mandonthierry/status/800712541634560001&quot;&gt;21 November 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
	&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, PhD graduates still face big challenges entering the world of work. This is why, as a PhD student, I decided to find out a bit more about hiring companies and their requirements by participating in four job fairs organized in Paris in November.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  
	&lt;div class=&quot;scalable scalable-16-9&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;scalable-content&quot;&gt;
			&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/J6scnDFKWRI&quot;  allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;em&gt;Video of PhDTalent explaining value of PhDs for a company [FR]&lt;/em&gt;
		&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;PhDTalent fair&lt;/b&gt;, two data science fairs: &lt;a href=http://www.datajob.fr/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;DATAJOB&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=http://forumdatadays.fr/programme/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Forum Data Paris&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  and one organized at &lt;a href=http://jnum.parisdescartes.fr/job-dating/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Journée Numérique&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;i&gt;Digital Day&lt;/i&gt; at University Paris Descartes.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
			At any job fair, meetup or a conference when we introduce ourselves as Computational Biologists, it is not always clear to other people what it actually means.
		&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;As a &lt;b&gt;Computational Biologist&lt;/b&gt; working on data analysis in the context of imunno-oncology, with some additional on-line training, I believe I have most of basic knowledge asked for post of data analyst or data scientist: working in R, Machine Learning, statistics, data visualization, git. However, this is not clear for people working out of research in biology and healthcare. There are so many flavors of computational biologists, using different tools and applying them to different fields of biology, that it crucial to state clear what we actually do given the desired job. Computational biologist profile also usually comes with weak points as lack of professional experience out of academia, no professional network, little experience with business and consumers. What is sure, &lt;b&gt;most of computational biologist&lt;/b&gt;, with some additional training to broad their technical horizons and with open mind, &lt;b&gt;have very attractive profile for many industries&lt;/b&gt;.
			&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;I have spend around 1-2 h of my time at each job fair, that took place during the week office hours. Even though, I didn&#39;t manage to talk to all companies, especially the most popular, where the line were very long, I managed to leave my CV to 15 companies and talk to around 20. Here is a little summary of each job fair. 
			&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/logo_PhDTalent.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=https://www.phdtalent.org/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PhDTalent fair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				PhDTalent attracted  more than 70 companies form different industries. These could be roughly  split into three groups: Biotech / Pharma, consulting, Policy, Robotics &amp; Data science &amp; Big data &amp; IT &amp; Computing. 

				There were presented a wide variety of different job offers. Some like Orange or L&#39;Oréal recruit for their PostDocoral programs.

				During the day, I have learned that some companies, during the &lt;b&gt;recruitment process&lt;/b&gt; can send applicants a &lt;b&gt;weekly challenge&lt;/b&gt; or test through up to &lt;b&gt;7 interviews&lt;/b&gt; for a R&amp;D position. In addition, I also spoke to various start-ups that generate diverse data; they need people to manage them and sometimes they do hope one PhD can replace data management team. I also encountered even very surprising job descriptions: one start-up in particular was looking to hire &lt;b&gt;bioinformatician to model hormone detection in the air by their humanoid robot&lt;/b&gt;. I am not sure if they correctly interpreted what the skills of a bioinformatician are ;) (For those who are not sure what bioinformatician does have a look at the article in &lt;a href=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4408859/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Frontiers of Genetics: Who qualifies to be bioinformatician?&lt;/a&gt;)
			&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/DATAJOBS.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/forumdata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Jobs forum at Bourse de Paris. Image credit to &lt;a href=http://www.datajob.fr/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;datajobs.fr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
			&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=http://forumdatadays.fr/programme/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Forum Data&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=http://www.datajob.fr/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Data Jobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Those two job fairs had splendid sponsors and a wide array of known companies present.
				Even though, it was not designed solely for PhD graduates I found companies representatives very enthousiastic and helpful  - perhaps reflecting vigor for the potential that the data industry has to offer. Key things that I took home from these events were that, of course, it is too early now for me to apply being mid-way through my PhD. However they recommended looking at role descriptions on company websites and keeping an eye out for events to get involved with. For example, some firms organize their own meetups where you have the opportunity to meet employees or work on mini projects for the company. I was also advised to attend &lt;a href=https://startupweekend.org/locations/europe/fr target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;startup weekends&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where many startup present at those and similar events hire actively. When trying to gather information about data analysis positions in an established beauty company with big R&amp;D sector, I was surprised to discover that they &lt;b&gt;only&lt;/b&gt; hire PhD graduates with at least three year experience working in company (whilst hiring engineers straight away). In contrast, Other companies were also looking for three years experience. However in practice, if companies are looking for people and you interview well, you have every chance of being hired. &lt;br&gt;Therefore, I buried my hopes to stay close to biology an healthcare, and analyze biological data. Probably for a first job, one needs to be more flexible than that.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=http://jnum.parisdescartes.fr/job-dating/ target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Journées numériques&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Among numerous activities of &lt;i&gt;Digital Day&lt;/i&gt; there were a little job fair organized. A few number of companies presented job offers. However, the &lt;i&gt;job offers in digital expertise&lt;/i&gt; was a bit misleading and most of jobs proposed were related to advanced computing, IT management, web marketing and communication.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;h3&gt;How to choose a company?&lt;/h3&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/office.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;It is very important issue. Let&#39;s imagine, you have a great profile, desired by many companies. How do you chose the company?&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;As a foreigner in France and academia-trained I do not have clear idea about model of functioning of different companies and possible advantage and disadvantages of specific setups.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;I encountered many consulting offices, where employees work actually for different companies to solve an issue or work on a project. I was told, their offer can seem very attractive at the first sight: variety of subjects, cutting edge technologies, big companies. However, they also are some drawbacks, as employees are hired by the consulting company, they are lured by the most attractive projects, but there is no guarantee to which one they will be associated because it depends a lot on client choice, and other available consultants. On the other hand, even a short contract in a company developing new technologies such as &lt;i&gt;Orange&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;Microsoft&lt;/i&gt; can be very good for your career, while consulting job can be easier to get but will not always meet your expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

					&lt;h3&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h3&gt;
					&lt;p&gt;Career transition is probably not easy, future is not all roses, but with some determination, I am pretty sure a &lt;b&gt;Camputational Biologist has great chances to find a well-paid job outside academia&lt;/b&gt;. Job market is very competitive and demands are high. Luckily for us, programming skills combined with capacity for analysis seem to be in high demand. There will be still some knowledge gaps, some unknowns, but our duty is to turn them into challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/horizon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
					&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

				&lt;/section&gt;
				&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/jobsCB/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/jobsCB/</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From Science to Data Science</title>
        <description>&lt;!DOCTYPE HTML&gt;
&lt;html lang=&quot;en-US&quot;&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
        &lt;meta charset=&quot;UTF-8&quot;&gt;
        &lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;refresh&quot; content=&quot;1; url=&quot;&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
            window.location.href = &quot;https://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/FromSciencetoDataScience/&quot;
        &lt;/script&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Page Redirection&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
        &lt;!-- Note: don&#39;t tell people to `click` the link, just tell them that it is a link. --&gt;
        If you are not redirected automatically, follow this &lt;a href=&#39;https://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/FromSciencetoDataScience/&#39;&gt;link to example&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/FromSciencetoDataScience</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/FromSciencetoDataScience</guid>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>Careers</category>
        
        <category>Data Science</category>
        
        <category>Data viz</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
        <category>FSctoDs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Outreach</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;


&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body&gt;

     &lt;style&gt;



      &lt;/style&gt;
 
      &lt;/body&gt;  
&lt;section&gt;
	&lt;h4&gt;Certificate in Business And Administration&lt;/h4&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;I has been four years CBA at Paris Descartes train and gather together talented students from different disciplines. Network build during this two-week workshop remains a strong point of all the participants.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;If you want to find out about my experience at CBA please &lt;a href=&quot;/thoughts/CBA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;check out my post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Here are some facts and figures we prepared with some CBA representatives and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PxGirard&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pierre Girard,&lt;/a&gt; the organiser of the Part I.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 

 

&lt;div class=&#39;tableauPlaceholder&#39; id=&#39;viz1479135570783&#39; style=&#39;position: relative&#39;&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#&#39;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#39;Tableau de bord 1 &#39; src=&#39;https:&amp;#47;&amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;#47;static&amp;#47;images&amp;#47;CB&amp;#47;CBA_2&amp;#47;Tableaudebord1&amp;#47;1_rss.png&#39; style=&#39;border: none&#39; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;object class=&#39;tableauViz&#39;  style=&#39;display:none;&#39;&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;host_url&#39; value=&#39;https%3A%2F%2Fpublic.tableau.com%2F&#39; /&gt; &lt;param name=&#39;site_root&#39; value=&#39;&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;name&#39; value=&#39;CBA_2&amp;#47;Tableaudebord1&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;tabs&#39; value=&#39;no&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;toolbar&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;static_image&#39; value=&#39;https:&amp;#47;&amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;#47;static&amp;#47;images&amp;#47;CB&amp;#47;CBA_2&amp;#47;Tableaudebord1&amp;#47;1.png&#39; /&gt; &lt;param name=&#39;animate_transition&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_static_image&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_spinner&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_overlay&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#39;display_count&#39; value=&#39;yes&#39; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;                &lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39;&gt;                    var divElement = document.getElementById(&#39;viz1479135570783&#39;);                    var vizElement = divElement.getElementsByTagName(&#39;object&#39;)[0];                    vizElement.style.width=&#39;824px&#39;;vizElement.style.height=&#39;3819px&#39;;                    var scriptElement = document.createElement(&#39;script&#39;);                    scriptElement.src = &#39;https://public.tableau.com/javascripts/api/viz_v1.js&#39;;                    vizElement.parentNode.insertBefore(scriptElement, vizElement);                &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/CBA_outreach</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/works/CBA_outreach</guid>
        
        <category>Tableau</category>
        
        <category>Infographic</category>
        
        <category>Communication</category>
        
        
        <category>works</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data and the Future of Healthcare</title>
        <description>&lt;!doctype html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
	&lt;meta name=&quot;description&quot; content=&quot;Urszula Czerwinska. About me, data science, big data, analytics, PhD&quot;&gt;

&lt;/head&gt;

 &lt;body&gt;

     &lt;style&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;    	
        
		body { background-color:blue; }
		.highlightme { background-color:#ccffe5; }
 &lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;/style&gt;
 
      &lt;/body&gt;  
      &lt;section&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pebourne&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Phil Bourne&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a founding Editor-in-Chief of PLOS Computational Biology and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sdsc.edu/~bourne/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Associate Director for Data Science (ADDS)&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nih.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Institutes of Health&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;His research focuses are countless: algorithms, text mining, machine learning, metalanguages, biological databases, and visualizations applied to problems in systems pharmacology, evolution, cell signaling, apoptosis, immunology and scientific dissemination coupled with education and public service.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Attendees  of ISMB 2016 in Orlando had the opportunity to interact with him at the workshop on Education in Bioinformatics (WEB) — ‘Exploiting Cloud and Virtual Resources for Training : Getting the Best Training in Computational Biology in an Era of Cloud Computing and Big Data’.&lt;/p&gt;


      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;
In this interview, Phil Bourne gives his opinion about Big Data era, the impact of data science and will impact biological research and healthcare. He also comments on frictions: between the corporate world and research, as well as formal training and citizen science. 
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;The list of your achievements and engagements is very long. Besides your academic ones, you also founded companies so you are familiar with corporate world. With regards to Data Science &amp; Big Data, it seems like there is a hype around them in companies right now. Do you think solutions developed for science can compete with the ones developed for big data with big money? Will academic and private Data Science work together or companies like Google will take a monopoly on data solutions?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Answer:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;Big data covers a big area — there is a need for government and private funder solutions, for company solutions and for hybrid solutions. Just as the market place benefits from government research that then gets translated into commercial products we will see the same with big data.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;highlightme&quot;&gt;Biomedical research and health care is a bit late in the game and has the disadvantage of not being born digital and so is relatively slow to respond.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Notwithstanding there is a lot of fundamental research which the private sector is not likely to do that will be done by government and private foundation funding and ultimately will prove to be of great value. Areas of provenance, standards, data wrangling and security are examples that come to mind.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Biological research is still under an ongoing digitization process. However an important number of wet lab biologist are still reluctant to learn how to use computational tools that would make their research more interesting and more quantitative. What message would you like to convey them?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Answer:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;The contributions of computation and other peoples data to the biomedical research enterprise cannot be ignored at this point. It should be embraced. &lt;span class=&quot;highlightme&quot;&gt;At the same time computational biologists have an obligation to make their methods and tools accessible to a broader audience.&lt;/span&gt; We need training programs that prepare students for a future where analytical techniques go hand-in-hand with more experimental approaches. Students need to be equally adept in silico, in vivo and in vitro.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;You are the founding Editor-in-Chief of PLOS Computational Biology, and you are enthusiastic about open science; open data and open education (like MOOCs and NIH training programs like Big Data to Knowledge). Can you explain why these matters are so important to you? Do you think non-scientist citizens should have equal access to scientific research and should actively participate?&lt;br&gt;
For instance, in Paris we had a data challenge (Epidemium) for cancer data, which involved engaging citizens to improve data management (databases) and data treatment. Do you think formal scientific education is necessary to participate in research?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Answer:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;The future of biomedical research involves a broader spectrum of data types and data which is publicly accessible. This creates unprecedented opportunities and we are already seeing the results. Examples are predicting healthcare outcomes from electronic health records either alone or in combination with other data. Use of mobility data to influence behavior etc. We need to foster the use of these data and the new methods emerging to use such open data. &lt;span class=&quot;highlightme&quot;&gt;Openness breaks down the traditional academic hierarchy and this is a good thing.&lt;/span&gt; We are doing what we can to foster new audiences to access and discover from the these data. The Open Science Prize and the Ideas labs we run with the NSF are examples.
&lt;blockquote&gt;While formal training is not necessary we must maintain the ethical standards and the rigor of the scientific method.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Do you think we are capable of coping with the amount of generated data? I have experienced in my own research that dealing even with medium size datasets can be problematic and many questions can be asked when looking for data from different angles. Is there a threat that with big data we could miss important questions? Some leaders of big data businesses say that we should slow the rate of data generation as data storage is costly and we are not able to analyse all these data. What’s your opinion?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Answer:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;This question is getting at data sustainability and maintenance and we have much work to do as a community here. We do not have a good handle on the rate of data generation, how to determine what to keep and what to discard, how to make the community aware of the persistence of particular types of data and many more issues. In the end we have to make decisions about cost vs benefit. In business the model is clearer — if we can leverage the data for the benefit of the company keep it, otherwise discard it. In academia there is a legacy of data preservation irrespective of perceived current value and the value cannot necessarily be measured in monetary terms. We need to develop metrics and best practices to define our data and subsequently make preservation decisions based upon these supporting data.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
 
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Today Big data, tomorrow…? What will be the next big step for health research?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Answer:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;The patient will become the center of the health care system as opposed to early health care (the physician) and today (the health care organization). The patient/participant will be empowered by a usable version of their own health record and the biomedical research which has used that record. They will interpret it themselves and whole new industries will appear to help them interpret the data and make decisions with the assistance of health care providers. Healthcare providers and healthcare industries will need to adjust to this new reality.
From a research perspective, systems based approaches will become more accepted and mainstream and be used as predictive tools Machine learning will figure more prominently.
Neuroscience will grow further as we explore the basis of consciousness and other aspects of the human condition. The relationship of health to the environment will be facilitated by the availability of large public environmental datasets and much more. Last but not least is the use of computational techniques and associated data in first response situations, notably concerning pandemics.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vision of data and healthcare outlined by Phil Bourne seem to be pretty optimistic. It is easy to see that the world of Data Science is complex but it is not lacking opportunities. This provides a lot of hope to researchers and students in the field of computational biology. As a community our mission is to seek opportunities in order to make the most of this universe; to explore it and to find new solutions for improving healthcare. Now is the ideal time to come forward with any ideas you have been sitting on — the potential benefits of data solutions are now more real than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;We extend our thanks to Phil Bourne for participating in this interview. Phil Bourne is a founding Editor-in-Chief of PLOS Computational Biology, which manages this collaborative blog.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: &lt;/strong&gt;Any views expressed are those of the author, not necessarily those of PLOS.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;footer&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on July 22, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/plos-comp-biol-field-reports-2016/data-and-the-future-of-healthcare-interview-with-phil-bourne-ismb16-db5ab9b296d4&quot;&gt;View the original&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
		   &lt;/section&gt;
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//s7.addthis.com/js/300/addthis_widget.js#pubid=ra-584ec4ce89deed84&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; 
&lt;!-- Go to www.addthis.com/dashboard to customize your tools --&gt; &lt;div class=&quot;addthis_inline_share_toolbox&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 
&lt;/html&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/interviewPhilBourne</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://urszulaczerwinska.github.io/thoughts/conferenceISMB2016/interviewPhilBourne</guid>
        
        
        <category>thoughts</category>
        
        <category>conferenceISMB2016</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
